<TEI xml:lang="eng" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Nandapur Plate of 169 GE</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Original EpiDoc Encoding for Siddham</resp>
          <persName ref="part:daba">
            <forename>Dániel</forename>
            <surname>Balogh</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Conversion of encoding for DHARMA</resp>
          <persName ref="part:daba">
            <forename>Dániel</forename>
            <surname>Balogh</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>EpiDoc encoding for DHARMA of parts not yet encoded for Siddham</resp>
          <persName ref="part:daba">
            <forename>Dániel</forename>
            <surname>Balogh</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>intellectual authorship of edition</resp>
          <persName ref="part:argr">
            <forename>Arlo</forename>
            <surname>Griffiths</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName ref="part:daba">
            <forename>Dániel</forename>
            <surname>Balogh</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>DHARMA</authority>
        <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
        <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00054</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
            <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Dániel Balogh &amp; Arlo Griffiths.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
            <idno/>
            <altIdentifier type="Siddham">
              <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00054</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary/>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <p>
Noteworthy shapes of M, ṅha.
Line 4: -svāmine: the ne has a special shape, apparely meant to reinforce the fact that the akṣara marks the end of a clause, a fact also indicated by following space.
Line 18: shape of gg in svargge.</p>
            </handDesc>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The project DHARMA has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC)
                        under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant
                        agreement no 809994).</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <schemaRef key="EGDv01" type="guide" url="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-02888186"/>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="bib" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9\-\_]+)" replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/1633743/erc-dharma/items/tag/$1">
          <p>Public URIs with the prefix bib to point to a Zotero Group Library named
                            ERC-DHARMA whose data are open to the public.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="part" matchPattern="([a-z]+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml#$1">
          <p>Internal URIs using the part prefix to point to person elements in the
                            <ref>DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml</ref> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change status="draft" when="2020-11-03" who="part:axja">Updating toward the encoding template v03</change>
      <change status="draft" when="2020-08-12" who="part:argr">further revisions after discussion with part:daba</change>
      <change status="draft" when="2020-08-08" who="part:argr">started manual revision of file imported by part:daba; removed editorial punctuation, inserted space elements, inserted abbr elements, inserted avagrahas, revised readings on the basis of RTI</change>
      <change status="draft" when="2020-08-04" who="part:daba">Initial import: harmonising file structure with DHARMA inscription template v02. Text and comments as inherited from the Siddham archive of January 2019, unless otherwise indicated (by a name and date in the comment). Comments are offered "as is" and do not represent a thoroughly considered or researched opinion.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:space="preserve">
    <body>
      <div type="edition" xml:lang="san-Latn">
        <p><pb n="1r"/><lb n="1"/>svasty amvila-grāmāgrahārāt sa-viśvāsam adhikaraṇaM <space/> jaṅgoyikā-grāme brāhmaṇottarān saṁvyavahā<lb break="no" n="2"/>ryy-ādi-kuṭumvinaḥ kuśalam anuvarṇṇya bodhayanti likhanti ca <space/></p>
        <p>vijnāpayati naḥ viṣaya-pati-chattramahaḥ<lb n="3"/>I<unclear>cch</unclear>āmy ahaṁ sva-puṇyābhivr̥ddhaye <space/> nanda-vaitheya-khaṭāpūraṇāgrahārika-cchāndoga-kāśyapa-sagottra-brāhmaṇa

<lb break="no" n="4"/>-<gap quantity="2" reason="illegible" unit="character"/>-svāmine <space/> pañca-mahā-yajña-pravarttanāya khila-kṣettra-kulya-vā<unclear>pa</unclear>-<subst>
            <del>tu</del>
            <add place="overstrike">ca</add>
          </subst>tuṣṭayaṁ kkrītvātisraṣṭuM<lb n="5"/>yuṣmad-viṣaye ca <space/> samudaya-vāhyādya-stamva-khila-kṣettrāṇāṁ <space/> śaśvad-ācandrārka-tāraka-bhojyā<supplied reason="omitted">nā</supplied><lb break="no" n="6"/>m akṣaya-nīvyā<surplus>ḥ</surplus> dvi-dīnārikya-kulya-vāpa-vikkrayo 'nuvr̥ttas tad arhatha <space/> matto 'ṣṭau dīnārān upa<lb break="no" n="7"/>saṁgr̥hya jaṅgoyikā-grāme khila-kṣettra-kulya-vāpa-catuṣṭayam akṣaya-nīvyās tāmra-paṭṭena dātum iti</p>
        <p><lb n="8"/>yataḥ pustapāla-pradyotasiṅha-vandhudāsayor a<add place="below" rend="mark">va</add>dhāraṇayāvadhr̥tam astīha viṣaye <space/> samudaya<lb break="no" n="9"/>-vāhyādya-stamva-khila-kṣettrāṇām akiñcit-pratika<space type="descender"/>rāṇāṁ dvi-dīnārikya-kulya-vāpa-vikkrayo 'nuvr̥ttaḥ<lb n="10"/>Evam-vi<unclear>dho</unclear>tpratikara-khila-kṣettra-vikraye ca na kaś cid rājārttha-virodhaḥ dīyamāne tu parama-bhaṭṭāraka<lb break="no" n="11"/>-pādānāṁ dharmma-ṣaḍ-bhāgāvāptis tad dīyatām ity etasmād viṣaya-pati-chattramahād aṣṭau dīnārān upa<lb break="no" n="12"/>saṁgr̥hya <space/> jaṅgoyikā-grāme <space type="descender"/> gorakṣita-tāmra-paṭṭa-dakṣiṇena <space/> gopāli-bhogāyā<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> paścimena khila<lb break="no" n="13"/>-kṣettra-kulya-vāpa-catuṣṭayaṁ dattaM <space/> <abbr>ku</abbr> <num value="4">4</num> <space/></p>
        <p>te yūyam evaṁ viditvā kuṭumvināṁ karṣaṇāvirodhi-sthāne <lb n="14"/>darvvī-karmma-hastenāṣṭaka-navaka-nalābhyām apaviñchya <space/> cira-kāla-sthāyi-tuṣāṅgārādi-cihnaiś catur-ddi<lb break="no" n="15"/>ṅ-niyamita-s<unclear>ī</unclear>mānaṁ kr̥tvā dāsyatha <space/> datvā cākṣaya-nīvī-dharmmeṇa śaśvat-kālam anupālayiṣyatha<pb n="1v"/><lb n="16"/>varttamāna-bhaviṣyaiś ca saṁvyavahāribhir etad dharmmāpekṣayānupālayitavyam iti <space/> Uktañ ca bhaga<lb break="no" n="17"/><unclear>vatā vyā</unclear>se<supplied reason="lost">na</supplied> <space/></p>
        <lg met="anuṣṭubh" n="1">
          <l n="a"><supplied reason="lost">sva-da</supplied>ttāṁ para-dattāṁ vā</l>
          <l n="b">yo hareta vasundharāṁ</l>
          <l n="c">sa viṣṭhāyāṁ kr̥mir bhūtvā</l>
          <l n="d">pitr̥bhiḥ saha <lb n="18"/>pacyate <space/></l>
        </lg>
        <lg met="anuṣṭubh" n="2">
          <l n="a"><supplied reason="lost">ṣa</supplied>ṣṭ<unclear>i</unclear> varṣa-sahasrāṇi</l>
          <l n="b">svar<unclear reason="eccentric_ductus">gg</unclear>e modati bhūmidaḥ <space/></l>
          <l n="c">Ākṣeptā cānumantā ca</l>
          <l n="d">tāny eva na<lb break="no" n="19"/>rake vaseT <space/></l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <abbr>saṁ</abbr>
          <space/>
          <num value="169">100 60 9</num>
          <space/>
          <abbr>vai</abbr>
          <abbr>śu</abbr>
          <abbr>di</abbr>
          <num value="7">7</num>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="apparatus">
        <listApp>
          <app loc="1">
            <lem>adhikaraṇaM</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01 bib:Sircar1965_02">adhikaraṇ<choice>
                <sic>ā</sic>
                <corr>a</corr>
              </choice>M</rdg>
            <note>Reading <foreign>ṇā</foreign> here would imply that the akṣara has a different shape from all other cases of <foreign>ṇā</foreign> in this inscription, which show a clockwise stroke at the bottom to make the <foreign>ā</foreign> (e.g. in line 9 <foreign>pratikarāṇāṁ</foreign>). By contrast, we can avoid the need to make any emendation by simply reading the expected <foreign>ṇa</foreign>, which does not seem problematic if we compare the forms of <foreign>ṇa</foreign> and M observed, e.g., in line 8 <foreign>avadhāraṇayā</foreign>, line 4 <foreign>atisraṣṭuM</foreign>, line 13 <foreign>dattaM</foreign>.</note>
          </app>
          <app loc="1">
            <lem>saṁvyavahā<lb break="no" n="2"/>ryy-</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01 bib:Sircar1965_02">saṁvyavahā<lb break="no" n="2"/>ry-</rdg>
          </app>
          <app loc="2">
            <lem source="bib:Sircar1965_02">bodhayanti likhanti</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01">bodhaya<choice>
                <sic>nti</sic>
                <corr>ti</corr>
              </choice> likha<choice>
                <sic>nti</sic>
                <corr>ti</corr>
              </choice></rdg>
            <note>Majumdar proposes to emend to <foreign>bodhayati likhati</foreign>, but he has not understood that <foreign>adhikaraṇam</foreign> is the subject of the sentence; the editorial note 1 on p. 55 of Majumdar's article provides a manner to escape from the necessity of emendation, but likewise misunderstands <foreign>adhikaraṇam</foreign> as object. Sircar refrains from making the emendation in the text, although he proposes it in a note (p. 382 n. 2), where he correctly explains the situation as follows: <q>Plural number was used through confusion apparently because the <foreign>adhikaraṇa</foreign> or board of administration consisted of several members: cf. <foreign>vijñāpayati naḥ</foreign> below.</q></note>
          </app>
          <app loc="3">
            <lem>-brāhmaṇa-</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01 bib:Sircar1965_02">-brāhmaṇā-</rdg>
            <note>The akṣara that was read <foreign>ṇā</foreign> by Majumdar and Sircar but is read <foreign>ṇa</foreign> here has the same shape as the one read thus in <foreign>adhikaraṇaM</foreign> in line 1. See the apparatus entry thereon.</note>
          </app>
          <app loc="4">
            <lem>kkrītvāti°</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01 bib:Sircar1965_02">krītvāti°</rdg>
          </app>
          <app loc="6">
            <lem>-nīvyā<surplus>ḥ</surplus></lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01">-nīvyāḥ</rdg>
            <rdg source="bib:Sircar1965_02">-nīvyā</rdg>
            <note>Sircar's reading is a silent emendation. Removing the visarga is justified by the fact that we find <foreign>akṣaya-nīvyā</foreign> in parallel passages in the <ref target="DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00049.xml">Baigram plate</ref>, l. 5, and the <ref target="DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00052.xml">Paharpur plate</ref>, l. 9.</note>
          </app>
          <app loc="10">
            <lem>-vi<unclear>dho</unclear>pratikara-</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01 bib:Sircar1965_02">-vidhotpratikara-</rdg>
            <note>We find <foreign>-vidhāpratikara-</foreign> in the parallel passage in the <ref target="DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00049.xml">Baigram plate</ref>, l. 12. With reference to a term <foreign>udbalika</foreign> (<bibl>
                <ptr target="bib:Sircar1966_01"/>
                <citedRange>348</citedRange>
              </bibl>), Sircar argues (<bibl rend="omitname">
                <ptr target="bib:Sircar1965_02"/>
                <citedRange unit="page">383</citedRange>
                <citedRange unit="note">3</citedRange>
              </bibl>) that <foreign>-vidha-utpratikara-</foreign> is acceptable because the otherwise unattested word <foreign>utpratikara</foreign> could mean the same same as <foreign>apratikara</foreign> and <foreign>akiñcitpratikara</foreign>. Although the very unclear akṣara <foreign>dho</foreign> could equally well be read as <foreign>dhā</foreign> to take us one step closer to <foreign>-vidhāpratikara-</foreign>, we would still be stuck with an intrusive <foreign>t</foreign> to be removed by emendation, and so I accept Sircar's explanation. Even if <foreign>utpratikara</foreign> is otherwise unattested, <foreign>ut</foreign> as a negative prefix is relatively well attested (e.g., <foreign>utkaca</foreign>, <foreign>uddāma</foreign>).</note>
          </app>
          <app loc="12">
            <lem source="bib:Sircar1965_02">gopāli-bhogāyā<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied></lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01">gopāli-bhogāyā</rdg>
          </app>
          <app loc="15">
            <lem>-s<unclear>ī</unclear>mānaṁ</lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01">-saṁmānaṁ</rdg>
            <rdg source="bib:Sircar1965_02">-paṁmānaṁ</rdg>
            <note>Sircar's reading must be a printing error.</note>
          </app>
          <app loc="19">
            <lem source="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01">
              <num value="7">7</num>
            </lem>
            <rdg source="bib:Sircar1965_02">
              <num value="8">8</num>
            </rdg>
            <note>Majumdar's edition as printed contains the reading <foreign>7</foreign>, which is corrected to <foreign>8</foreign> in the <title>Additions and Corrections</title> to this article in EI. Obviously Sircar failed to take notice of that correction when he copied Majumdar's text for his own edition.</note>
          </app>
        </listApp>
      </div>
      <div resp="part:argr" type="translation">
        <p n="1-2">Hail! From the <foreign>agrahāra</foreign> of the village Amvila, the <supplied reason="subaudible">members of the</supplied> council which enjoys <supplied reason="subaudible">the king’s</supplied> confidence, having offered greetings to the administrator(s) and other landholders <supplied reason="explanation">
            <foreign>kuṭumbin</foreign>
          </supplied> at the village Jaṅgoyikā, brahmins being foremost among them, inform and write:</p>
        <p n="2-7">The district chief Chattramaha respectfully requests from us: 
<q>In order to increase my own merit, I wish to buy four <foreign>kulyavāpa</foreign>s of uncultivated land and give <supplied reason="subaudible">them</supplied> to the Chandoga (i.e., Sāmavedic) Brahmin <gap reason="illegible"/>svāmin of the Kāśyapa gotra and <supplied reason="explanation">resident</supplied> of the Khaṭāpūraṇa <foreign>agrahāra</foreign> in the Nanda territory <supplied reason="explanation">
              <foreign>vīthi</foreign>
            </supplied>, for the purpose of the regular performance of the five great sacrifices. And in your district, it is customary to sell for two <foreign>dīnāra</foreign>s a <foreign>kulyavāpa</foreign> of uncultivated land that is without revenue charges and covered with original shrubs,  as permanent endowment to be enjoyed in perpetuity as long as the moon, the sun and the stars <supplied reason="subaudible">will last</supplied>. Therefore, be so kind as to accept from me eight <foreign>dīnāra</foreign>s and to give four <foreign>kulyavāpa</foreign>s of uncultivated land in the village Jaṅgoyikā with a copper-plate of permanent endowment.</q></p>
        <p n="8-11">Wherefore it has been ascertained through the investigation of the record-keepers Pradyotasiṁha and Bandhudāsa that it is customary in this district to sell for two <foreign>dīnāra</foreign>s a <foreign>kulyavāpa</foreign> of uncultivated land that is without revenue charges and covered with original shrubs, yielding no tax at all; and that there is no conflict whatsoever with the interest of the king in selling such uncultivated land that yields no tax; but that, when it is given, his majesty obtains a sixth of the merit; so that it ought to be given.</p>
        <p n="11-13">After eight <foreign>dīnāra</foreign>s had been accepted from this district chief Chattramaha, four <foreign>kulyavāpa</foreign>s of uncultivated land have been given in the village Jaṅgoyikā, to the south of Gorakṣita’s gift land <supplied reason="explanation">
            <foreign>tāmrapaṭṭa</foreign>
          </supplied>, to the west of Gopālibhogā <supplied reason="explanation">Gopālī’s property</supplied>. 4 <foreign>ku<supplied reason="lost">lyavāpa</supplied></foreign>.</p>
        <p n="13-16">You there <supplied reason="explanation">mentioned at the start of the grant</supplied>, having understood <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied>, shall separate them off using two reeds, eight by ninefold with the ladle-work <supplied reason="explanation">
            <foreign>darvīkarma</foreign>
          </supplied> cubit in a place that does not conflict with the cultivation of the landholders; shall make a boundary delimited in the four directions with long-lasting markers such as <supplied reason="subaudible">pots filled with</supplied> chaff or charcoal; shall make the donation and shall protect it in perpetuity according to the rule of a permanent endowment. And out of deference to this rule it is to be protected by present and future administrators.</p>
        <p n="16-19">And it has been said by the Lord Vyāsa:</p>
        <p n="1" rend="stanza">The one who would steal land given by himself or another becomes a worm in shit and is cooked with his ancestors.</p>
        <p n="2" rend="stanza">The giver of land resides sixty thousand years in heaven; the one who challenges <supplied reason="explanation">a donation</supplied> as well as the one who approves <supplied reason="explanation">of the challenge</supplied> will reside as many <supplied reason="explanation">years</supplied> in hell.</p>
        <p n="19">Year 169, <supplied reason="explanation">month of</supplied> Vaiśākha, waxing day 7.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="commentary">
        <p>Line 1: the expression <foreign>saviśvāsam adhikaraṇam</foreign> may be compared with <ref target="DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00039.xml">Raktamālā charter, no. 1</ref>, l. 21; <ref target="DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00057.xml">Raktamālā charter, no. 2</ref>, l. 20; and with <ref target="DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00032.xml">Damodarpur plate of the time of Budhagupta (163 GE)</ref>, ll. 2–3.</p>
        <p>Line 9: the qualification <foreign>ādya-stamba</foreign> is found also in the <ref target="DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00049.xml">Baigram plate</ref>, ll. 4–5, the only other inscription in the group of Gupta-period land-sale grants with the precise string of characteristics found here; the interpretation <q>covered with original shrubs</q> is that of D.C. Sircar <bibl rend="omitname">
            <ptr target="bib:Sircar1965_02"/>
            <citedRange unit="page">382</citedRange>
            <citedRange unit="note">4</citedRange>
          </bibl>, accepted by R. Furui <bibl rend="omitname">
            <ptr target="bib:Furui2020_01"/>
            <citedRange unit="page">42–43</citedRange>
          </bibl>.
</p>
        <p>Line 14: on <foreign>darvīkarma</foreign>, see <bibl>
            <ptr target="bib:Griffiths2018_02"/>
            <citedRange unit="page">43, 53</citedRange>
            <citedRange unit="note">32</citedRange>
          </bibl>.</p>
        <p>Lines 14–15: the phrase <foreign>cira-kāla-sthāyi-tuṣāṅgārādi-cihnaiś catur-ddiṅ-niyamita-sīmānaṁ kr̥tvā</foreign> recalls expressions in the <ref target="DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00049.xml">Baigram plate</ref> and the <ref target="DHARMA_INSBengalCharters00051.xml">Tāvīra grant</ref>. See <bibl>
            <ptr target="bib:Griffiths2018_02"/>
            <citedRange unit="page">42–43</citedRange>
          </bibl>.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <p>First edited, with English translation and photos of estampages of the plate, by N. G. Majumdar (<bibl rend="omitname">
            <ptr target="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01"/>
          </bibl>); basically the same text was published again, with addition of some explanatory footnotes, by D. C. Sircar (<bibl rend="omitname">
            <ptr target="bib:Sircar1965_02"/>
            <citedRange unit="item">48A</citedRange>
            <citedRange unit="page">382-384</citedRange>
          </bibl>). The text is re-edited here by Arlo Griffiths and Dániel Balogh based on RTIs of the plate, using a digital edition created by Dániel Balogh for the Siddham project as starting point. (Since the readings in that digital edition don't differ from the printed editions, its variant readings are not recorded in our apparatus.)</p>
        <listBibl type="primary">
          <bibl n="B">
            <ptr target="bib:Balogh+al2019_01"/>
          </bibl>
          <bibl n="S">
            <ptr target="bib:Sircar1965_02"/>
            <citedRange unit="item">48A</citedRange>
            <citedRange unit="page">382-384</citedRange>
          </bibl>
          <bibl n="M">
            <ptr target="bib:Majumdar1935-1936_01"/>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="secondary">
          <bibl>
            <ptr target="bib:Furui2020_01"/>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <ptr target="bib:Griffiths2018_02"/>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
