<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Paḷḷivāḍa grant of Viṣṇuvardhana II</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding</resp>
               <persName ref="part:daba">
                  <forename>Dániel</forename>
                  <surname>Balogh</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>intellectual authorship of edition</resp>
               <persName ref="part:daba">
                  <forename>Dániel</forename>
                  <surname>Balogh</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>DHARMA</authority>
            <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
            <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSVengiCalukya00011</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported
              Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit
              https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to
              Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View,
              California, 94041, USA.</p>
                  <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Dániel Balogh.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc><!-- only the handDesc can be filled in at this stage -->
            <msDesc><!-- //// NB: the msIdentifier had to be added for validation purposes ///. It will be edited later with the metadata spreadsheet -->
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                  <idno/>
                  <!-- don't modify this -->
                  <!--<altIdentifier type="PEM"><idno type="corpus">CalE20</idno></altIdentifier>-->
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents><!-- describe the intellectual content of an inscription -->
                  <summary><!-- //// NOT MANDATORY  ////--></summary>
                  <!-- offers the possibility to give a summary of the inscription's content -->
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <p>Halantas. M: l2. abhivarddhitānāM is a simplified J shape raised to headline height.l20 AmāvāsyāyāM: looks like a largish circle at headline height CHECK PHOTOS.</p>
                     <p>Original punctuation. The opening symbol is a dextrorse spiral of about 1.5 full turns, with a tail at the top left.</p>
                     <p>Other palaeographic observations. In the correction in line 10, the omitted character is added right above the spot where it must go, and a kākapada in the shape of a + sign is inserted right below that spot. In l20, sū looks like sya with a short loop: instead of adding a stroke to the well-shaped u marker, the entire bottom of the well is bent to the left.</p>
                     <p>Le and lo are written in the cursive form (as used in earlier / more northerly scripts?): instead of attaching markers to the sides of a fully rounded la, the stem is not bent to the left and down, but curved at the top sharply back in le (l11 sakalendur) and the curve extended beyond the stem in lo (l2 loka).</p>
                     <p>The anusvāra is shifted to the right in l7 pijaṁrita, encoded as a scribal error since normally the anusvāra is in its expected position.

                <!-- The script name(s) will be inserted here at a later stage from the metadata spreasheet. At this stage, you can mention here in a free-text paragraph any characteristics of the writing observed more than once in this inscription that seem unusual/uncommon or otherwise noteworthy given the general characteristics of the script in question. See EG 11.2. --></p>
                     <!-- If you need to identify individual hands (EG §7.5/) in addition to one or more paragraphs of general palaeographic description, wrap <summary> around the <p> or <p>s above, and, outside <summary>, create <handNote> elements for each hand as follows:
                <summary><p><p/></summary>
                <handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand1"></handNote>
                <handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand2"></handNote>
              -->
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The project DHARMA has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC)
                        under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant
                        agreement no 809994).</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <schemaRef type="guide"
                    key="EGDv01"
                    url="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-02888186"/>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="bib"
                       matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9\-\_]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/1633743/erc-dharma/items/tag/$1">
               <p>Public URIs with the prefix bib to point to a Zotero Group Library named
                            ERC-DHARMA whose data are open to the public.</p>
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="part"
                       matchPattern="([a-z]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml#$1">
               <p>Internal URIs using the part prefix to point to person elements in the
                            <ref>DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml</ref> file.</p>
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="part:axja" when="2020-11-03" status="draft">Updating toward the encoding template v03</change>
        <change who="part:daba" when="2020-08-14" status="draft">Encoded hand description, bibliography and commentary from earlier comments</change>
        <change who="part:daba" when="2020-04-23" status="draft">Initial encoding of the file</change>
         <!-- Add a <change> entry for each significant change to the file. -->
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:space="preserve">
    <body>



<div type="edition" xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:83225 maturity:83213">
<div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  <ab><lb
n="1"/>śrī-viṣamasiddhi</ab>
</div>
<div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
<ab><pb

n="1r"/><fw n="1r" place="left"><num value="1">1</num></fw><lb
n="01"/><g type="spiralR"/>
<lb
n="02"/>svasti</ab>
<p><lb
n="1"/>śrīmatāṁ sakala-bhuvana-saṁstūyamāna-mānavya-sagotrāṇāṁ <lb
n="2"/>hāritī-putrāṇāṁ sapta-loka-mātr̥bhir mmātr̥bhir abhivarddhitānāM kārtti<lb
n="3" break="no"/>keyā<space type="binding-hole"/>nugrahāvāpta-kalyāṇa-parampar<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>nāṁ bhagavan-nārāy<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>ṇa-pra<lb
n="4" break="no"/>sādāsādita-varāha-lāñcchanātmīkr̥tāśeṣa-bhūbhr̥tāṁ bhū-bhr̥tāṁ ivācala-sthi<lb
n="5" break="no"/>tīnāṁ Aśvamedhāvabhr̥tha-snānāpanīta-kali-malānāṁ caḷukyānāṁ kulam a<pb

n="1v" break="no"/><lb
n="6" break="no"/><unclear>laṁ</unclear>ka<choice><sic>r</sic><corr>ri</corr></choice>ṣṇoḥ śrī-kīrttivarmmaṇaḥ praṇaptā sakalāvan<orig>ī</orig>-pati-makuṭa-taṭa-ghaṭita<lb
n="7" break="no"/>-maṇi-mayūkha-puṁja-pi<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied>ja<surplus>ṁ</surplus>rita-caraṇa-yuga<orig>ḷ</orig>asya śrī-viṣṇuvarddhana-mahārājasya <lb
n="8"/>naptā śa<space type="binding-hole"/>kti-traya-s<subst><del rend="corrected">ā</del><add place="overstrike">a</add></subst>māsāditāśeṣa-bhū-maṇḍalādhipateḥ sva-guṇā<lb
n="9" break="no"/>nurakta-pra<space type="binding-hole"/>kr̥ti-saṁpādita-sarvva-saṁpadaḥ śrī-jayasi<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied>ha-vallabha-<choice><sic>v</sic><corr>m</corr></choice>ahārājasya <lb
n="10"/>priya-bhrātur a<add place="above" rend="mark">ne</add>ka-yuddha-labdha-vijayālaṁkr̥ta-śarīrasyendra-bhaṭṭārakasya <pb

n="2r"/><fw n="2r" place="left"><num value="2">2</num></fw><lb
n="11"/>priya-tanayaḥ samadhigata-pañca-mahāśabdaḥ sakalendur iva sakala-kalādhi<lb
n="12" break="no"/>ṣṭhāno vi<del>ṣa</del><space type="binding-hole"/>ṣṇur iva śrī-nivāsaḥ śrīmān viṣṇuvarddhana-mahārājaḥ gudrahāra<lb
n="13" break="no"/>-viṣa<space type="binding-hole"/>ye Aṟutaṅkūrāśraye pa<choice><unclear>ḷḷ</unclear><unclear>dd</unclear><unclear>ḍḍ</unclear></choice>i<unclear>v</unclear>āḍa-grāmam adhivasataḥ <lb
n="14"/>sarvvān evam <choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>jñāpayati</p>
<p part="I">yathā Asanapura-v<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>s<choice><sic>th</sic><corr>t</corr></choice>avyasya kāśy<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>pa-gotrasya <lb
n="15"/>nūvucūṭṭi-trivedasya taittirīya-sabrahmacāriṇaḥ veda-vedāṁgetihā<pb

n="2v" break="no"/><lb
n="16" break="no"/>sa-purāṇa-nyāyāneka-dharmmaśāstr<subst><del rend="corrected">ā</del><add place="overstrike">a</add></subst>-vidaḥ Agniṣṭomādi-pauṇḍarīka-pa<lb
n="17" break="no"/>ryyantāneka-kratu-yaṣṭuḥ dhruvaśarmmaṇaḥ pautrāya veda-vedāṁga-vidaḥ <lb
n="18"/>doci<space type="binding-hole"/>śarmmaṇaḥ putrāya Adhīta-veda-dvayāya dhruvaśarmmaṇe <lb
n="19"/>Asmin grāme Asmat-puṇyābhivr̥<surplus>r</surplus>ddhaye <choice><sic>A</sic><corr>Ā</corr></choice>tmano vijaya-rājya-pañca<lb
n="20" break="no"/>me saṁ<orig>vv</orig>atsare phā<unclear>l</unclear>gu<orig>ṇ</orig>a-māse AmāvāsyāyāM sūryya-gra<supplied reason="omitted">ha</supplied>ṇa-nimi<supplied reason="lost">tte</supplied>
</p>
</div>
</div>





<div type="apparatus">
  <div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
    <listApp>
      <app loc="3">
        <lem>-nārāy<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>ṇa-</lem>
        <note>According to Fleet's note, the superfluous <foreign>ā</foreign> marker was partially erased. Based on photos of the cleaned original plate, this does not seem to be the case. Nonetheless, Fleet may be correct; for the premodern correction of <foreign>śāstrā</foreign> to <foreign>śāstra</foreign> in line 16, he notes that the correction was made by paring down the copper on both sides of the unwanted stroke, but in the estampage, only the stroke is visible. In the photo of that locus, a thinning of the superfluous stroke is clear, and the surface around it seems slightly different from the rest of the surface. None of these signs are, however, discernible here.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="12">
        <lem>vi<del>ṣa</del><space type="binding-hole"/>ṣṇur</lem>
        <note>This line is above the hole, so regular-sized characters could have fit here. The engraver clearly started engraving <foreign>ṣṇu</foreign> (but got only as far as <foreign>ṣa</foreign>), then realised the subcript components would not fit, and therefore hammered out this character and started again to the right of the hole.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="14">
        <lem>kāśy<choice><sic>ā</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>pa-</lem>
        <rdg source="bib:Fleet1878_01"><choice><sic>kaśyāpa</sic><corr>kāśyapa</corr></choice></rdg>
        <note>The first <foreign>ā</foreign> is faint but clear in the photo of the original.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="18">
        <lem>dhruvaśarmmaṇe</lem>
        <note>After this word, there are three faint dots one below the other. These may be random, but it is also possible that an initially engraved <foreign>ṇaḥ</foreign> was corrected to <foreign>ṇe</foreign> by cancelling the <foreign>visarga</foreign> and adding a vowel mark.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="19">
        <lem>-rājya-</lem>
        <note>Fleet's edition omits this word, but his translation includes it.</note>
      </app>



    </listApp>
  </div>

</div>




<div type="translation" resp="part:daba">
  <div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
<p n="1-14">Greetings. The great-grandson of His Majesty Kīrtivarman, who was eager to adorn the family of the majestic Caḷukyas—who are of the Mānavya <foreign>gotra</foreign>, which the entire world praises, who are sons of Hāritī, who are cherished by the Mothers who are the mothers of the seven worlds, who have by the favour of Kārttikeya attained hereditary good fortune, who have turned all kings into their dependents by means of the Boar emblem acquired through the grace of the divine Nārāyaṇa, whose presence is as permanent as that of mountains, and who have cast off the filth of the Kali <supplied reason="subaudible">age</supplied> by bathing in the purificatory ablutions <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>avabhr̥tha</foreign></supplied> of the Aśvamedha sacrifice—; grandson of His Majesty King <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>mahārāja</foreign></supplied> Viṣṇuvardhana, whose pair of lotus feet were engilded by a mass of beam clusters from gems fitted to the surfaces of the crowns of all <supplied reason="explanation">other</supplied> kings; dear son of Indra Bhaṭṭāraka, whose body was adorned by victories achieved in numerous battles and who was the beloved brother of His Majesty King <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>mahārāja</foreign></supplied> Jayasiṁha Vallabha, who reigned supreme <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>adhipati</foreign></supplied> over of the entire circle of the earth obtained by means of his three powers <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>śakti-traya</foreign></supplied>, and whose wealth has been entirely consigned to his subjects <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>prakṛti</foreign></supplied> who <supplied reason="subaudible">in turn</supplied> are impressed <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>anurakta</foreign></supplied> by his virtues; the majestic King <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>mahārāja</foreign></supplied> Viṣṇuvardhana <supplied reason="explanation">II</supplied>, who has attained the five great sounds<note>The expression <foreign>pañca-mahāśabda</foreign> probably refers to being honoured by the sound of five musical instruments, but may also mean five titles beginning with “great”. See <bibl><ptr target="bib:Fleet1888_01"/><citedRange unit="page">296-298</citedRange><citedRange unit="note">9</citedRange></bibl> for a discussion.</note>, a vessel of all skills <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>kalā</foreign></supplied> as the full moon <seg rend="pun">is comprised of all its digits</seg>, the abode of royal majesty <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>śrī</foreign></supplied> as Viṣṇu <seg rend="pun">is the shelter of <supplied reason="explanation">the goddess</supplied> Śrī</seg>, commands everyone inhabiting the village Paḷḷivāḍa subordinate to <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>āśraye</foreign></supplied> <supplied reason="explanation" cert="low">the town</supplied> Aṟutaṅkūr in Gudrahāra district <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>viṣaya</foreign></supplied> <supplied reason="subaudible">as follows</supplied>:</p>
<p n="14-20">
To wit, in this village, in the fifth year of my victory <supplied reason="explanation">i.e. reign</supplied>, at the new moon of the month of Phālguna, on the occasion of a solar eclipse, <supplied reason="lost">I have donated</supplied> to Dhruvaśarman who has studied the two Vedas, son of  Dociśarman, who was familiar with the Vedas and Vedāṅgas, grandson of Dhruvaśarman of the Kāśyapa <foreign>gotra</foreign> and the Taittirīya school, a nūvucūṭṭi scholar of the three Vedas and a resident of the monastery<note>It seems likely that <foreign>sthāna</foreign> does not simply mean a place or locality here. In a discussion of the <ref target="DHARMA_INSVengiCalukya00010.xml">Puloṁbūra Grant</ref>, Sankaranarayanan (<bibl rend="omitname"><ptr target="bib:Sankaranarayanan1977_01"/><citedRange>74</citedRange></bibl>) suggests that <foreign>sthāna</foreign> may be equivalent to <foreign>ghaṭikā-sthāna</foreign>, but the <foreign>ghaṭikā</foreign> is mentioned as clearly separate in the <ref target="DHARMA_INSVengiCalukya00008.xml">Niḍupaṟu Grant</ref>. I therefore assume that <foreign>sthāna</foreign> means a temple complex where Brahmans reside, semantically (though perhaps not physically) distinct from the <foreign>ghaṭikā</foreign> as an institution of learning.</note> of Asanapura who was familiar with the Vedas, Vedāṅgas, Itihāsas, Purāṇas, Nyāya and numerous legal treatises <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>dharmaśāstra</foreign></supplied> and who performed numerous sacrifices from the Agniṣṭoma all the way to the Pauṇḍarīka, <gap reason="lost"/>
</p>
  </div>
</div>



<div type="translation" xml:lang="fra" source="bib:Estienne-Monod2008_01">
  <div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
<p n="1-14">Prospérité ! l’arrière petit-fils de l’illustre Kīrtivarman, ornement de la lignée des Calukya, illustres, honorés dans l’univers entier, du même <foreign>gotra</foreign> que les descendants de Manu, fils de Hāritī, rendus prospères par les Mères, mères des sept mondes, doués d’une prospérité ininterrompue, octroyée par la faveur de Kārtikeya, qui eurent tous les rois sous leur pouvoir grâce au signe du sanglier, faveur accordée par le bienheureux Nārāyaṇa, demeures inébranlables comme les montagnes, eux dont les souillures de l’âge de Kali furent lavées par le bain purificatoire de l’<foreign>aśvamedha</foreign>, le petit-fils du grand roi illustre Viṣṇuvardhana, dont les deux pieds sont colorés par le rouge doré des faisceaux de rayons des pierres précieuses serties sur l’orbe des diadèmes des seigneurs de la terre entière, le cher fils d’Indra Bhaṭṭāraka, dont le corps est orné par les victoires remportées dans les nombreux combats, cher frère du grand roi illustre Jayasiṁha Vallabha, maître suprême du cercle entier de la terre, conquis grâce à <supplied reason="subaudible">ses</supplied> trois pouvoirs, qui gagna toutes les richesses grâce à sa nature, qui fut attaché à la vertu, l’illustre grand roi Viṣṇuvardhana, qui a perçu les cinq grands sons,<note>Mention la plus ancienne de cette épithète et la seule appliquée à un roi (N. D. E.).</note> - il rassemblait tous les arts comme la pleine lune rassemble toutes ses portions,<note><foreign>śabdaśleṣa</foreign> reposant sur le mot <foreign>kalā</foreign> qui désigne les beaux arts, que connaît le roi, et les portions de la lune.</note> comme Viṣṇu, refuge de Śrī,<note><foreign>śabdaśleṣa</foreign> reposant sur le mot <foreign>śrī</foreign> qui désigne la fortune du roi et l’épouse de Viṣṇu.</note> - à tous ceux qui résident dans le village de Paḷḷivāḍa, mitoyen d’Aṟutaṅkūr, dans le viṣaya de Gudrahāra, ordonne ceci :</p>
<p n="14-20">au petit-fils de Dhruvaśarman, qui habite Asanapura, du gotra de Kaśyapa, disciple dans l’école de Taittirīya de Nūvucūṭṭi, qui connaît les trois Veda, qui connaît les Veda, les Vedāṁga, les Ithihāsa, les Pūraṇa, la doctrine du Nyāya et les nombreux Dharmaśāstra, qui a accompli de nombreux sacrifices, à commercer par l’<foreign>agniṣṭoma</foreign>,<note>Sur ce sacrifice, cf. insc. n°8. Mentionné aussi in insc. nos 7 et 8.</note> jusqu’au <foreign>pauṇḍarīka</foreign>,<note>Sur ce sacrifice, cf. insc. n°7. Mentionné aussi in insc. nos 8, 15, 16 et 20.</note> au fils de Dociśarman, qui connaît les Veda et Vedāṁga, à Dhruvaśarman, dans ce village, pour l’accroissement de nos mérites, la cinquième année de notre règne victorieux, au mois de Phālguṇa, le jour de la nouvelle lune, à l’occasion de l’éclipse de soleil.
</p>

  </div>
</div>




<div type="commentary">
<p>There is no image of the seal in either set of estampages consulted, and its text is reproduced here as reported by Fleet, without indication of any unclarity or loss. The first two plates of the grant are extant, the rest are lost. The writing starts on the recto of the first plate. Foliation numbers are in the left margin, roughly at the level of the binding hole, below the level of line 3 on plate 1, and at the baseline of line 3 on plate 2. The first plate begins with two short marginal lines distinct from the body text. Fleet does not read the mangala symbol (in the top left corner, aligned with l1) and prints svasti (aligned with l2) at the beginning of l1. I believe śrī belongs with the mangala symbol in the marginal field. The third text line begins directly below svasti; the first two lines are indented to make space for the opener; the second line's indent is larger, because śrī encroaches on the space where this line could have been started.</p>
<p>Each extant plate has five lines.</p>
</div>



<div type="bibliography">
  <p>Edited from the original by J. F. FLeet (<bibl rend="omitname"><ptr target="bib:Fleet1878_01"/></bibl>), with estampages of the plates and translation. The date is revised in <bibl><ptr target="bib:Fleet1891_05"/><citedRange>8-9</citedRange></bibl>. Subsequently noticed in <bibl><ptr target="bib:ARIE1962-1963"/><citedRange unit="page">49</citedRange><citedRange unit="appendix">A/1962-1963</citedRange><citedRange unit="item">16</citedRange></bibl>. The present edition by Dániel Balogh is based on a collation of Fleet's text with his published facsimiles and inked impressions from Sir Walter Elliot's collection.<note>Scans of these impressions were obtained by Emmanuel Francis from the Edinburgh University Library, the Bibliothèque nationale de France and the British Museum.</note>
  </p>
  <listBibl type="primary">
    <bibl n="JFF"><ptr target="bib:Fleet1878_01"/></bibl>
<!-- one <bibl/> per item of primary bibliography -->
  </listBibl>
  <listBibl type="secondary">
    <bibl><ptr target="bib:Fleet1891_05"/><citedRange>8-9</citedRange></bibl>
    <bibl><ptr target="bib:ARIE1962-1963"/><citedRange unit="page">49</citedRange><citedRange unit="appendix">A/1962-1963</citedRange><citedRange unit="item">16</citedRange></bibl>
<!-- one <bibl/> per item of secondary bibliography -->
  </listBibl>
</div>



    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
