<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xml:lang="eng" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Guḍivāḍa plates (set 1) of Jayasiṁha I</title>
        <!--Alt title "Ādivāsa, Jayasiṁha I" in PEM's corpus.-->
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoding</resp>
          <persName ref="part:daba">
            <forename>Dániel</forename>
            <surname>Balogh</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>intellectual authorship of edition</resp>
          <persName ref="part:daba">
            <forename>Dániel</forename>
            <surname>Balogh</surname>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>DHARMA</authority>
        <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
        <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSVengiCalukya00005</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported
              Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit
              https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to
              Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View,
              California, 94041, USA.</p>
            <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Dániel Balogh.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <!-- only the handDesc can be filled in at this stage -->
        <msDesc>
          <!-- //// NB: the msIdentifier had to be added for validation purposes ///. It will be edited later with the metadata spreadsheet -->
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
            <idno/>
            <!-- don't modify this -->
            <!--<altIdentifier type="PEM"><idno type="corpus">CalE14</idno></altIdentifier>-->
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <!-- describe the intellectual content of an inscription -->
            <summary><!-- //// NOT MANDATORY  ////--></summary>
            <!-- offers the possibility to give a summary of the inscription's content -->
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <p>Halantas. T: l1 śrīmaT, smallish ta shape with long stem and no headmark; note use of T in what is normally viewed as a compound. l1 vāsakāT, same. M: all instances are unclear in the scan. Perhaps a small ma shape with the right-hand arm elongated, but perhaps simplified into a single stroke like a check mark or a Latin capital J.</p>
              <p>Original punctuation. The opening symbol seems to be a fairly small dextrorse spiral, transcribed by Somasekhara Sarma as oṁ.</p>
              <p>Other palaeographic observations. Subscript m is usually cursively simplified into a loop lying on its side.
                <!-- The script name(s) will be inserted here at a later stage from the metadata spreasheet. At this stage, you can mention here in a free-text paragraph any characteristics of the writing observed more than once in this inscription that seem unusual/uncommon or otherwise noteworthy given the general characteristics of the script in question. See EG 11.2. --></p>
              <!-- If you need to identify individual hands (EG §7.5/) in addition to one or more paragraphs of general palaeographic description, wrap <summary> around the <p> or <p>s above, and, outside <summary>, create <handNote> elements for each hand as follows:
                <summary><p><p/></summary>
                <handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand1"></handNote>
                <handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand2"></handNote>
              -->
            </handDesc>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The project DHARMA has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC)
                        under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant
                        agreement no 809994).</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <schemaRef key="EGDv01" type="guide" url="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-02888186"/>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="bib" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9\-\_]+)" replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/1633743/erc-dharma/items/tag/$1">
          <p>Public URIs with the prefix bib to point to a Zotero Group Library named
                            ERC-DHARMA whose data are open to the public.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="part" matchPattern="([a-z]+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml#$1">
          <p>Internal URIs using the part prefix to point to person elements in the
                            <ref>DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml</ref> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change status="draft" when="2020-11-03" who="part:axja">Updating toward the encoding template v03</change>
      <change status="draft" when="2020-08-14" who="part:daba">Encoded hand description, bibliography and commentary from earlier comments</change>
      <change status="draft" when="2020-04-02" who="part:daba">Initial encoding of the file</change>
      <!-- Add a <change> entry for each significant change to the file. -->
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:space="preserve">
    <body>
      <div rendition="class:83225 maturity:83213" type="edition" xml:lang="san-Latn">
        <div n="A" type="textpart">
          <head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
          <ab><lb n="1"/>śrī-sarvvasid<unclear>dh</unclear>i</ab>
        </div>
        <div n="B" type="textpart">
          <head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
          <pb n="1r"/>
          <p><pb n="1v"/><lb n="1"/><g type="spiralR"/>svasti śrīmaT-kallūra-vāsakāT svāmi-bhaṭṭāraka-pāda-padma-prasādā<lb break="no" n="2"/>vāptarājyānāṁ hārītī-priya-putrāṇāṁ mānavya-sagotrāṇām aśva<lb break="no" n="3"/>medha-yā<space type="binding-hole"/>jināṁ calukyānāṁ kula-jaladhi-samudbhūta-rāja-ratna<lb break="no" n="4"/>sya sakala<space type="binding-hole"/>-jagad-ārtti-hara-karmmaṇaḥ śrī-kīrttivarmmaṇaḥ priya<lb break="no" n="5"/>-naptā sva-pitur anūna-guṇa-gaṇod<supplied reason="omitted">d</supplied>yotita-rociṣṇor aidaṁyugīna-ma<lb break="no" n="6"/>hāviṣṇoḥ viṣṇuvarddhana-mahārājasya priya-tanayaḥ
<pb n="2r"/><lb n="7"/>pravarddhamāna-pratāpopanamita-ripu-nr̥pati-makuṭa-taṭa-ghaṭita-ma<lb break="no" n="8"/>ṇi-mayū<choice>
              <sic>k</sic>
              <corr>kh</corr>
            </choice>a-mañjarī-puñja-piñjarita-caraṇāravinda-yugalaḥ para<lb break="no" n="9"/>ma-brahmaṇyo mātā-pitr̥-pādānuddhyātaḥ śrī-p<orig>ri</orig>thivī-jayasiṁha<lb break="no" n="10"/>-vallabha-ma<space type="binding-hole"/>hārājaḥ pḻakki-viṣayam adhivāsinaḥ kuṭumbinaḥ <lb n="11"/>samājñāpayati</p>
          <p>yathā maudgalya-sagotrasya kauthuma-chando<lb break="no" n="12"/>ga-sabrahmacāriṇaḥ kumāraśarmmaṇaḥ pautrābhyāṁ vasuśarmmaṇaḥ<pb n="2v"/><lb n="13"/>putrābhyā<orig>M</orig> vinayaśa<choice>
              <sic>ma</sic>
              <corr>rmma</corr>
            </choice>-viṣṇuśarmmābhyā<unclear>ṁ</unclear> trisahasra-pāragābhyāM <lb n="14"/>ṣaṭ-karmma-niratābhyāM Asmad-āyur-ārogya-jaya-yaśo<orig>t</orig>i<lb break="no" n="15"/>vr̥ddhaye <space type="binding-hole"/> soma-grahaṇe Udaka-pūrvvaṁ kr̥tvā Ādivāse <lb n="16"/>punnāgapa<space type="binding-hole"/>dra<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied> <choice>
              <sic>vastādiṁ</sic>
              <corr>vasatiṁ</corr>
            </choice> kr̥tvā kuḻivāṭaka-kṣetra-sahitaṁ pa<lb break="no" n="17"/>ścima-khaṇḍaḥ sarvva-kara<surplus>ṁ</surplus>-parīhāreṇāgrahāraṁ kr̥tvā Ā-candrārka<lb break="no" n="18"/>-tārakam mayā saṁprattaM<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> tad viditvā yathocitaṁ bhāga-bhoga<pb break="no" n="3r"/><lb break="no" n="19"/>m upanayantaḥ sukha<choice>
              <sic>ḥ</sic>
              <corr>ṁ</corr>
            </choice> prativasatha<surplus>ḥ</surplus><supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> kaiścid api bādhā na kartta<lb break="no" n="20"/>vyā<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> vyāsa-gītāḥ</p>
          <lg met="anuṣṭubh" n="1">
            <l n="a">bahubhir vvasudhā dattā</l>
            <l n="b">bahubhiś cānupālitā</l>
            <l n="c"><lb n="21"/>yasya ya<space type="binding-hole"/>sya yadā bhūmiḥ</l>
            <l n="d">tasya tasya tadā phalaM</l>
          </lg>
          <lg met="anuṣṭubh" n="2">
            <l n="a"><lb n="22"/>sva-dattāṁ <space type="binding-hole"/> para-dattāṁ vā</l>
            <l n="b">yatnād rākṣa yudhiṣṭhira</l>
            <l n="c">mahīṁ ma<lb n="23"/>h<orig>i</orig>matāṁ śreṣṭha</l>
            <l n="d">dānāc chreyo <supplied reason="subaudible">’</supplied>nupālanaM</l>
          </lg>
          <p>Ājñapti<unclear>ḥ</unclear> <lb n="24"/>parameśvaravarmmā<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> <abbr>saṁ</abbr> <num value="18">10 8</num> <abbr>he</abbr> <num value="8">8</num> <abbr>di</abbr> <num value="15">10 5</num></p>
          <pb n="3v"/>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="apparatus">
        <div n="A" type="textpart">
          <head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
        </div>
        <div n="B" type="textpart">
          <head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
          <listApp>
            <app loc="15">
              <lem>Ādivāse</lem>
              <note>Somasekhara Sarma emphasises that the reading may also be Āḍivāse. While this is possible in principle, I prefer to read this as a Sanskrit word rather than an uninterpretable toponym.</note>
            </app>
            <app loc="16">
              <lem>punnāgapa<space type="binding-hole"/>dra<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied> <choice>
                  <sic>vastādiṁ</sic>
                  <corr>vasatiṁ</corr>
                </choice></lem>
              <rdg source="bib:SomasekharaSarma1955-1956_01">punnāgapadravastādiṁ</rdg>
              <note>Somasekhara Sarma's editor suggests <foreign>punnāgapadraḥ vasatiṁ</foreign>, apparently construing <foreign>punnāgapadraḥ</foreign> as the subject (logical object) of the donation, whose verb he emends to <foreign>saṁprattaḥ</foreign>. See my commentary.</note>
            </app>
          </listApp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div resp="part:daba" type="translation">
        <div n="A" type="textpart">
          <head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
        </div>
        <div n="B" type="textpart">
          <head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
          <p n="1-12">Greetings from the residence at majestic Kallūra.
The dear grandson of His Majesty Kīrtivarman, whose actions dispel the suffering of all the world, a jewel of a king arisen from the ocean that is the family of the Calukyas—who attained kingship by grace of the lotus feet of Lord Bhaṭṭāraka <supplied cert="low" reason="explanation">Mahāsena</supplied>, who are the darling sons of Hārītī, who are of the Mānavya <foreign>gotra</foreign> and who have performed the Aśvamedha sacrifice; the dear son of King <supplied reason="explanation">
              <foreign>mahārāja</foreign>
            </supplied> Viṣṇuvardhana, a veritable Supreme Viṣṇu of this epoch, who is resplendent because he is illuminated by a host of virtues not inferior to <supplied reason="subaudible">those of</supplied> his father; His Majesty the supremely pious Pr̥thivījayasiṁha Vallabha, who was deliberately appointed <supplied reason="subaudible">as heir</supplied> by his mother and father, whose pair of lotus feet are engilded by a mass of beams sprayed from gems fitted to the surfaces of the crowns of enemy kings forced to bow by his ever-increasing valour—
commands the householders <supplied reason="explanation">
              <foreign>kuṭumbin</foreign>
            </supplied> of Pḻakki district <supplied reason="explanation">
              <foreign>viṣaya</foreign>
            </supplied> <supplied reason="subaudible">as follows</supplied>:</p>
          <p n="12-20">to wit, on the occasion of an eclipse of the moon I, in order to further augment our <supplied reason="explanation">my</supplied> vitality, health, victory and glory, have <seg cert="low">allotted to</seg> Vinayaśarman and Viṣṇuśarman—grandsons of Kumāraśarman of the Maudgalya <foreign>gotra</foreign> and of the Kauthuma-Chandoga school; sons of Vasuśarman; who have fully perused the three thousand <supplied reason="explanation">
              <foreign>trisahasra-pāraga</foreign>
            </supplied><note>See <bibl>
                <ptr target="bib:Sankaranarayanan1977_01"/>
                <citedRange>145-146</citedRange>
              </bibl> for a discussion of the term.</note> and are devoted to the six duties <supplied reason="explanation">of a Brahmin</supplied>—<supplied cert="low" reason="subaudible">their</supplied> <seg cert="low">prior residence</seg> Punnāgapadra <seg cert="low">to be their abode</seg> and, having first performed a libation, donated <supplied reason="subaudible">to them</supplied> the western part <supplied cert="low" reason="explanation">of that village</supplied> including the Kuḻivāṭaka field, converted into a rent-free holding <supplied reason="explanation">
              <foreign>agrahāra</foreign>
            </supplied> by a remission of all taxes, <supplied reason="explanation">to remain their property</supplied> as long as the moon, sun and stars <supplied reason="explanation">remain</supplied>.<note>My interpretation of the details of the donated property and the statements about the abode of the donees is tentative. Somasekhara Sarma assumes that Ādivāsa is a topnym, while I prefer to understand it as "prior residence."</note>
Having learned this, you shall continue living in equanimity, providing for them the appropriate dues <supplied reason="explanation">
              <foreign>bhāga</foreign>
            </supplied> and commodities <supplied reason="explanation">
              <foreign>bhoga</foreign>
            </supplied>. And let no-one pose an obstacle <supplied reason="explanation">to their enjoyment of their rights</supplied>. <supplied reason="subaudible">The following verses were</supplied> sung by Vyāsa:</p>
          <p n="1" rend="stanza">
Many <supplied reason="explanation">kings</supplied> have granted land, and many have preserved it <supplied reason="explanation">as formerly granted</supplied>. Whosoever at any time owns the land, the fruit <seg rend="pun">reward <supplied reason="explanation">accrued of granting it</supplied></seg> belongs to him at that time.</p>
          <p n="2" rend="stanza">
O Yudhiṣṭhira, diligently preserve land that has been donated, whether by yourself or another. O best of land-possessors, preserving <supplied reason="explanation">a grant</supplied> is superior to making a grant.
</p>
          <p n="23-24">
The executor <supplied reason="explanation">
              <foreign>ājñapti</foreign>
            </supplied> is Parameśvaravarman. Year 18, the 8th <supplied reason="subaudible">fortnight</supplied> of the winter <supplied reason="explanation">hemanta</supplied> <supplied reason="subaudible">season</supplied>, day 15.
</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div source="bib:Estienne-Monod2008_01" type="translation" xml:lang="fra">
        <div n="A" type="textpart">
          <head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
        </div>
        <div n="B" type="textpart">
          <head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
          <p n="1-12">Om ! Prospérité ! De la résidence de l’illustre Kallūra,
le cher petit-fils de l’illustre de Kīrtivarman, joyau des rois nés dans l’océan qu’est la lignée des Calukya,<note>Ces deux composés : <foreign>kula-jalanidhi-samudbhūta-rāja-ratnasya sakala-jagad-ā[r*]tti-hara-karmmaṇaḥ śrī-kīrttivarmaṇaḥ</foreign>, qualifient aussi le <foreign>biruda</foreign> Kīrtivarman dans l’insc. n° 15. On retrouve également le premier dans les insc. nos 16, avec la variante <foreign>kula-jaladhi°</foreign> , et dans l’insc. n°19 avec la variante <foreign>kula-jalanidhi-samutpanna°</foreign>. Le second apparaît dans les insc. nos 15 et 17. Ces composés glosent toujours le <foreign>biruda</foreign> Kīrtivarman.</note> destructeur des souffrances de tout l’univers, <supplied reason="subaudible">rois</supplied> qui ont obtenu leur royaume à la faveur des pieds de lotus du seigneur Bhaṭṭāraka, fils de Hārītī, du même <foreign>gotra</foreign> que les descendants de Manu, qui pratiquent l’<foreign>aśvamedha</foreign>,
le cher fils du grand roi Viṣṇuvardhana, grand Viṣṇu du <foreign>yuga</foreign>,<note>Nous avons rencontré ce composé dans trois autres inscriptions du même roi (insc. nos 15, 16, 17). Nous pouvons formuler l’hypothèse qu’il s’agit d’un dérivé à <foreign>vr̥ddhi</foreign> initiale sur la base du syntagme  <foreign>idaṁ yugam</foreign>. Nous serions alors en présence d’un exemple assez intéressant de délocutivité, idam référant au locuteur, donc au discours. Ce composé fait allusion à un exploit de Viṣṇu : à la fin du Kaliyuga, Viṣṇu s’incarne en Kalki et remet les méchants sur la voie du bien.</note> brillant et luisant d’une multitude de vertus qui n’étaient pas inférieures à celle de son père, l’illustre grand roi Pr̥thivī Jayasiṁha Vallabha, dont les deux pieds de lotus sont rougis par les bourgeons que sont les rayons émis par les pierres serties sur l’orbe des diadèmes des rois ennemis, que son auguste majesté fait courber, très pieux, méditant aux pieds de sa mère et de son père, ordonne aux chefs de famille habitant le <foreign>viṣaya</foreign> de Pḻakki :</p>
          <p n="12-20">je donne aux deux petit-fils de Kumāraśarman, du même <foreign>gotra</foreign> que les Maudgalya, disciple de l’école des Kauthuma Chandoga, aux deux fils de Vasuśarman, à Vinayaśarman et à Viṣṇuśarman, qui connaissent parfaitement les Trisahasra, dévoués à leurs six devoirs,<note>Sur les six devoirs cf. <title>Manusmr̥ti</title>, X, 75.</note> en vue de l’accroissement de notre vie, santé, victoire et gloire, lors de l’éclipse de lune, après avoir fait une libation d’eau, à Ādivāsa, après avoir fait ?,<note>Ce passage demeure obscur.</note> une parcelle à l’ouest, jointe à des terrains de Kuḻivāṭaka, exemptés de toute taxe, en qualité d’<foreign>agrahāra</foreign>, pour aussi longtemps qu’existeront la lune et les étoiles. Sachant cela, ceux qui procurent la jouissance de ce lot vivent dans le bonheur. Aucune charge ne doit lui être imposée. Les vers de Vyāsa <supplied reason="subaudible">sont</supplied> :</p>
          <p n="1" rend="stanza">beaucoup ont donné une terre, beaucoup l’on protégée, celui qui possède la terre en possède le fruit.</p>
          <p n="2" rend="stanza">Qu’elle soit donnée par lui ou par un autre, ô Yudhiṣṭhira, protège avec force la terre ! ô meilleur des possesseurs de la terre, la protection de la terre est plus méritoire que le don.</p>
          <p n="23-24">L’exécuteur est Parameśvaravarman. La huitième quinzaine de Hemanta, dans la dix-huitième année <supplied reason="explanation">de règne</supplied>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="commentary">
        <p> Some notes on the relationship of the three grants edited in (<bibl rend="omitname">
            <ptr target="bib:SomasekharaSarma1955-1956_01"/>
          </bibl>, hereafter: SS) based on his summary on p136 and filled out with place names. SS's editor finds his argument unconvincing; he notes that both the village and the donee names are different in the first two grants, and the third grant seems to be a later modified copy of the second.</p>
        <p>Grant 1 = <ref target="DHARMA_INSVengiCalukya00005.xml">this grant</ref>, called Ādivāsa by PEM
<list>
            <item>SS:the second grant, creating a new agrahāra from land cut off on the one side from (the western portion of) Ādivāsa and on the other side from Guḍivāḍa</item>
            <item>Text: he grants some land, possibly cut off from (the western part of?) Punnagapadra and including Kulivataka-ksetra. The donees are Vinayasarman and Visnusarman, sons of Vasusarman, grandsons of Kumarasarman of the Maudgalya gotra.</item>
            <item>In the actual text: Ādivāse punnāgapadra vastādiṁ kr̥tvā kuḻivāṭaka-kṣetra-sahitaṁ paścima-khaṇḍaḥ ... saṁprattaM</item>
            <item>As emended by S.Sarma: Ādivāse punnāgopavana-gr̥ha-sthānaṁ kr̥tvā kuḻivāṭaka-kṣetra-sahitaṁ paścima-khaṇḍaṁ ... saṁprattam (in this, the punnāgopavana thing is offered tentatively)</item>
            <item>As emended by S. Sarma's editor: Ādivāse punnāgapadraḥ vasatiṁ kr̥tvā kuḻivāṭaka-kṣetra-sahitaḥ paścima-khaṇḍaḥ ... saṁprattaḥ</item>
            <item>I now think that the intended meaning is something like: Ādivāse(/aṁ) punnāgapadre(/aṁ) vasatiṁ kr̥tvā kuḻivāṭaka-kṣetra-sahitaḥ paścima-khaṇḍaḥ ... saṁprattaḥ (or -sahitaṁ paścima-khaṇḍaṁ ... saṁprattaM; khaṇḍa can be both m and n). </item>
          </list>
</p>
        <p>Grant 2 = <ref target="DHARMA_INSVengiCalukya00006.xml">Guḍivāḍa plates (set 2)</ref>, called Kuḍivāḍa 1 by PEM
<list>
            <item>SS: the first grant, creating the village of Kuḍivāḍa/Guḍivāḍa or creating an agrahāra from that village</item>
            <item>Text: he settles them in Kudivada village, cutting off land from Kundura village. The donees are Svamiyasas and Visnuyasas, sons of Visnuyasas, grandsons of Mitrayasas. The donees further give one ninth of their land to their sister's son (bhāgineya) Visnusarman, who is of the Gavismi gotra and thus probably different from the Visnusarman in Grant 1.</item>
            <item>Actual text: kuḍivāḍa nāma grāmaḥ vasati kr̥tvā kundūra-grāma-simno dvātrāṅśa-nivarttanaṁ chitvā … sambrattaṁ</item>
          </list>
</p>
        <p>Grant 3 = <ref target="DHARMA_INSVengiCalukya00007.xml">Guḍivāḍa plates (set 3)</ref>, called Kuḍivāḍa 2 by PEM
<list>
            <item>SS: the third grant, compensating the donees (which ones?) by cutting off land again from the village of Kundūru.</item>
            <item>Text: same donation and donees as in Grant 2, but without the brother-in-law. (So why don't we assume this is the earlier version, and Grant 2 is a later re-issue of this one?)</item>
            <item>Actual text: kuḍivāḍa nāma grāmaḥ vasatiṁ kr̥tvā kundūra-grāma-sīmno pr̥thak-kr̥tya … dattaḥ</item>
            <item>If we assume this to be ungarbled, then it is clear that the village itself was given _and_ made their residence. But since this text does not say _what_ was separated off from Kundura, it may be garbled. However, the boundaries are set out, while they are not in Grant 2.</item>
          </list>
</p>
        <p>My conclusion as of 1 April 2020: I'll keep the nomenclature introduced by PEM. I cannot form an opinion whether S. Sarma is right to equate Kudivada to Kulivataka. Changed 2 April: but since the plates all come from a village now called Guḍivāḍa, it makes very good sense to assume that they are the same. I also have strong doubts that Ādivāsa is a place name, and even if I renamed this first set to Punnāgapadra, the other two sets would have to use the same internal place name. I find it better to name all three after the findspot.</p>
        <p>S.Sarma is right to point out that dating by season (l24) is very unusual at this late time. Another important observation of his is that since an eclipse of the moon must have taken place on a full-moon day, and the date is the 15th day of the last (8th) fortnight of winter, the months must have been reckoned as pūrṇimānta (unless the season change happened in the middle of a month, something I am not sure can be excluded).
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <p>Edited from the original plates by M. Somasekhara Sarma(<bibl rend="omitname">
            <ptr target="bib:SomasekharaSarma1955-1956_01"/>
            <citedRange unit="page">129-133</citedRange>
            <citedRange unit="item">A</citedRange>
          </bibl>), with estampages of the plates and photograph of the seal. The present edition by Dániel Balogh is based on a collation of Somasekhara Sarma's edition with his facsimiles.</p>
        <listBibl type="primary">
          <bibl n="MSS">
            <ptr target="bib:SomasekharaSarma1955-1956_01"/>
            <citedRange unit="page">129-133</citedRange>
            <citedRange unit="item">A</citedRange>
          </bibl>
          <!-- one <bibl/> per item of primary bibliography -->
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="secondary">
          <bibl/>
          <!-- one <bibl/> per item of secondary bibliography -->
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
