<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cevuru plates of Amma I</title>
            <!--ALT TITLE: -->
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding</resp>
               <persName ref="part:daba">
                  <forename>Dániel</forename>
                  <surname>Balogh</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>intellectual authorship of edition</resp>
               <persName ref="part:daba">
                  <forename>Dániel</forename>
                  <surname>Balogh</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>DHARMA</authority>
            <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
            <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSVengiCalukya00027</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported
              Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit
              https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to
              Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View,
              California, 94041, USA.</p>
                  <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Dániel Balogh.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc><!-- only the handDesc can be filled in at this stage -->
            <msDesc><!-- //// NB: the msIdentifier had to be added for validation purposes ///. It will be edited later with the metadata spreadsheet -->
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                  <idno/>
                  <!-- don't modify this -->
                  <!--<altIdentifier type="PEM"><idno type="corpus">CalE36</idno></altIdentifier>-->
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents><!-- describe the intellectual content of an inscription -->
                  <summary><!-- //// NOT MANDATORY  ////--></summary>
                  <!-- offers the possibility to give a summary of the inscription's content -->
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <p>Halantas resemble the regular consonants in their principal part, but have no headmark; instead, a sinuous line is attached to their top right, resembling a tilde with the right-hand end extended upward into a repha-like vertical stroke (possibly with a headmark there). It is my impression that this extension is a stylisation of the was subscript consonants are attached to primary consonants in conjuncts, with the implication that a character incorporating this stroke is attached to a non-akṣara. The body of M has a reduced body resembling an archaic ma but definitely different from the standard ma in this script, e.g. l3 pādānudhyātānāM. (In l34, phalaM is not quite clear but seems to have a much reduced body.) The body of N is like regular na, but slightly smaller, e.g. l22 ārādhitavāN.</p>
                     <p>Original punctuation marks are short, plain, raised vertical bars extending from head height down to about median height or above. The one after phalaM in l34 seems not to be raised but to float at median height.</p>
                     <p>Other palaeographic observations. Anusvāra is at headline height to the right of the akṣara to which it belongs, e.g. l1 śrīmatāṁ. It is separated from its akṣara by a line break in l16-17 kuṭu/ṁbinas; Chhabra refers to E Cālukya parallels in ll 29-30 of the <ref target="DHARMA_INSVengiCalukya00012.xml">Reyūru grant of Viṣṇuvardhana II</ref> (where, however, the dot in question may be something other than an anusvāra), and ll 61-62 of the Masulipatam plates of Amma <!--CHECK probably CalE49, add ref when encoded.-->. The stroke for medial e sometimes bends to the right and up, attached to the top of the consonant on the left (l20 sāhasena, l22 saṁpṛtair). In addition to these, Chhabra points out as unusual the o in l1 sagotrāṇāṁ, but I see nothing striking in it; Chhabra's point may be that the left-hand stroke in this case curls down and back to touch the body of the consonant. Subscript l (e.g. l6 vallabhendrasya, l16 guṇakkenallā°) is a simplified spiral continuing to the right in a notched horizontal line, then attached upward to the body of the main consonant. It sort of reminds me of the way halanta consonants are formed in this script, with what could be a halanta l turned 90 degrees to the right. </p>
                     <!-- The script name(s) will be inserted here at a later stage from the metadata spreasheet. At this stage, you can mention here in a free-text paragraph any characteristics of the writing observed more than once in this inscription that seem unusual/uncommon or otherwise noteworthy given the general characteristics of the script in question. See EG 11.2. -->
                     <!-- If you need to identify individual hands (EG §7.5/) in addition to one or more paragraphs of general palaeographic description, wrap <summary> around the <p> or <p>s above, and, outside <summary>, create <handNote> elements for each hand as follows:
                <summary><p><p/></summary>
                <handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand1"></handNote>
                <handNote xml:id="Pallava00001_hand2"></handNote>
              -->
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The project DHARMA has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC)
                        under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant
                        agreement no 809994).</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <schemaRef type="guide"
                    key="EGDv01"
                    url="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-02888186"/>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="bib"
                       matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9\-\_]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/1633743/erc-dharma/items/tag/$1">
               <p>Public URIs with the prefix bib to point to a Zotero Group Library named
                            ERC-DHARMA whose data are open to the public.</p>
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="part"
                       matchPattern="([a-z]+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml#$1">
               <p>Internal URIs using the part prefix to point to person elements in the
                            <ref>DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml</ref> file.</p>
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="part:axja" when="2020-11-03" status="draft">Updating toward the encoding template v03</change>
         <change who="part:daba" when="2020-08-24" status="draft">Initial encoding of the file</change>
         <!-- Add a <change> entry for each significant change to the file. -->
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:space="preserve">
    <body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="san-Latn" rendition="class:83225 maturity:83213">
<div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  <ab><lb
n="1"/>śrī-tribhuvanāṁkuśa</ab>
</div>
<div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
<pb

n="1r"/>
<p><pb

n="1v"/><lb
n="1"/>svasti<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> śrīmatāṁ sakala-bhuvana-saṁstūyamāna-mānavya-sagotrānāṁ <lb
n="2"/>hārīti-putrāṇāṁ kauśikī-vara-prasāda-labdha-rājyānāṁ mātr̥-gaṇa-pari<lb
n="3" break="no"/>pālitānāṁ svāmi-mahāsena-pādānudhyātānāM bhagavan-nārāyaṇa<lb
n="4" break="no"/>-prasāda-sa<space type="binding-hole"/>māsādita-vara-varāha-lāñchanekṣaṇa-kṣaṇa-vaśīkr̥tā<lb
n="5" break="no"/>rāti-ma<space type="binding-hole"/>ṇḍalānām aśvamedhāvabhr̥tha-snāna-pavitrīkr̥ta-vapu<lb
n="6" break="no"/>ṣāṁ cālukyā<space type="binding-hole"/>nāṁ kulam alaṁkariṣṇoḥ satyāśraya-vallabhendrasya kula-tila<lb
n="7" break="no"/>kāyamāna-svāsi-dhārā-namita-ripu-nr̥pati-makuṭa-taṭa-ghaṭita-maṇi-mayū<lb
n="8" break="no"/>kha-puṁja-piṁjarita-pāda-padma-yugalasya cālukya-bhīma-bhūpālasya pautraḥ <lb
n="9"/>sāsi-sannahana-sva-tanu-tulā-tulita-bhūri-bhāra-bhāsura-hema-rā<choice><orig>s</orig><reg>ś</reg></choice>i-mahā<pb

n="2r" break="no"/><lb
n="10" break="no"/>dāna-viśeṣā<choice><sic>ḍ</sic><corr>ḍh</corr></choice>yīkr̥ta-vipra-kula-kalpavr̥kṣasya samasta-bhuvanāśra<lb
n="11" break="no"/>ya-vijayādityasya putraḥ Amma-mahīpatir ggaṇḍaragaṇḍo rājamahe<lb
n="12" break="no"/>ndra Iti vikhyātaḥ dāyāda-timirodyad-dinakara-kiraṇāyamāna-bhāsurā<lb
n="13" break="no"/>si-sanāthī<space type="binding-hole"/>kr̥ta<surplus>ta</surplus>-dakṣiṇa-<choice><sic>bh</sic><corr>b</corr></choice>āhus sa<surplus>sa</surplus>rvva-lokāśraya-śrī-viṣṇuva<lb
n="14" break="no"/>rddhana-mahā<space type="binding-hole"/>rājādhirāja-parameśvara-parama-bhaṭṭārakaḥ parama-mā<lb
n="15" break="no"/>heśvaraḥ gu<space type="binding-hole"/>dravāra-viṣaya-nivāsino rāṣṭrakūṭa-pramukhān kuṭu<lb
n="16" break="no"/>ṁbinas samāhūyettham ājñāpayati<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied></p>
<p>viditam astu vaḥ guṇakkenallā<lb
n="17" break="no"/>para-nāmadheya-vijayāditya-mahārāja-prasādīkr̥ta-hasty-āroha<lb
n="18" break="no"/>ṇāvāpta-gudravāra-viṣaya-śrīmad-umikili nāma grāma-rāṣṭrakūṭa<pb

n="2v" break="no"/><lb
n="19" break="no"/>-m<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>hātmyasya konakula-candeyarājasya pautraḥ rājādityānuja-mano<lb
n="20" break="no"/>hitāryyasya putraḥ vemarājo nāma subhaṭaḥ sāhasena kali<lb
n="21" break="no"/>-yuga-<choice><sic>s</sic><corr>ś</corr></choice>ūdrako mat-pitaraṁ vijayāditya<supplied reason="omitted">ṁ</supplied> baddha-karppaṭakaḥ svāmi-bhakti<lb
n="22" break="no"/>r ārādhitavāN<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> tad-ārādhana-svāmi-bhakti-saṁp<choice><sic>r̥</sic><corr>rī</corr></choice>tair asmābhiḥ kumāra-vija<lb
n="23" break="no"/>yādityā<space type="binding-hole"/>nna-prā<choice><sic>s</sic><corr>ś</corr></choice>ana-nimitte kramāgata-siddhāyāṣṭa-gadyāṇa<lb
n="24" break="no"/>kaṁ paritya<space type="binding-hole"/>jya sarvva-kara-parihāra<surplus>ṁ</surplus>m umikilī-grāma-grāmaṇīs sa <lb
n="25"/>vemarāja<supplied reason="omitted">ḥ</supplied> kr̥taḥ<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied></p>
<p>grāma-dakṣiṇataḥ Ervvoka-cenu<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> Asyāvadhayaḥ<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> <lb
n="26"/>pūrvvataḥ vranta<g type="commaHigh">.</g> dakṣiṇataḥ dūdrupāka-sīmaiva<g type="commaHigh">.</g>
paścimataḥ rāca-cenu <lb
n="27"/>cāṇḍ<choice><sic>a</sic><corr>ā</corr></choice>la-kṣetraṁ ca<g type="commaHigh">.</g> Uttarataḥ koḍu<g type="commaHigh">.</g></p>
<p>grāmottara-diśi Aypa-Ervvoka-ce<pb

n="3r" break="no"/><lb
n="28" break="no"/>nu<g type="commaHigh">.</g> Asyāvadhayaḥ<g type="commaHigh">.</g> pūrvvataḥ koḍu<g type="commaHigh">.</g> dakṣiṇataḥ vanneṟu<g type="commaHigh">.</g> paścimataḥ <lb
n="29"/>koḍu<g type="commaHigh">.</g> Uttarataḥ kolani mulugu<g type="commaHigh">.</g></p>
<p xml:lang="tel-Latn">puṭṭi-nirugu saveraṁ Iruvadinālgu vuṭla-ni<lb
n="30" break="no"/>ṇḍṟāyam padu-gaṇḍu padeḻ dumu<g type="commaHigh">.</g> tamulaṁmula-tūmeṇḍu<g type="commaHigh">.</g></p>
<p>Asyopari na <lb
n="31"/>kenacid bā<space type="binding-hole"/>dhā karttavyā<supplied reason="subaudible">.</supplied> yaḥ karoti sa paṁca-mahā-pātaka-saṁyu<lb
n="32" break="no"/>kto bhava<space type="binding-hole"/>ti<g type="commaHigh">.</g> tathā ca vyāsenāpy uktaṁ<g type="commaHigh">.</g></p>
<lg n="1" met="anuṣṭubh">
<l n="a">bahubhir vvasudhā dattā</l>
<l n="b">bahu<lb
n="33" break="no"/>bhiś cānu<space type="binding-hole"/>pālitā</l>
<l n="c">yasya yasya yadā bhūmis</l>
<l n="d">tasya tasya tadā <lb
n="34"/>phalaM<g type="comma">.</g></l>
</lg>
<lg n="2" met="anuṣṭubh">
<l n="a">sva-dattāṁ para-dattāṁ vā</l>
<l n="b">yo hareta vasuṁdharāṁ</l>
<l n="c">ṣaṣṭiṁ varṣa-sa<lb
n="35" break="no"/>hasrāṇi</l>
<l n="d">viṣṭhāyāṁ jāyate k<choice><orig>ri</orig><reg>r̥</reg></choice>miḥ</l>
</lg>
<lg n="3" met="āryā">
<l n="ab">veṁgī-maṇḍala-rakṣa<choice><sic>no</sic><corr>ṇa</corr></choice>-bhuja-bala<lb
n="36" break="no"/>-kaṭakeśvaras samājñāptiḥ</l>
<l n="cd" real="+---+-+--+--++----+">bhaṭṭa-ni<unclear>ravadya-sa</unclear>ntati-bhaṭṭa-mahā<unclear>kāla</unclear>-viracitaṁ</l>
</lg>
<pb

n="3v"/>
</div>
</div>





<div type="apparatus">
  <div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
   <listApp>
      <app loc="3">
        <lem>-mahāsena-</lem>
        <note>As Chhabra duly notes, there is a superfluous dot high above <foreign>se</foreign>.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="4">
        <lem>-varāha-</lem>
        <note>As Chhabra duly notes, there is a superfluous dot at mid-height between <foreign>va</foreign> and <foreign>rā</foreign>.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="13">
        <lem>-sanāthī°</lem>
        <note>According to Chhabra, there is a superfluous dot above <foreign>sa</foreign>. This is not visible in the scanned rubbing.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="13">
        <lem>sa<surplus>sa</surplus>rvva-</lem>
        <note>As Chabra notes, emendation is not strictly necessary, as the first <foreign>sa</foreign> may be interpreted as a pronoun. I believe a scribal error is more likely.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="22">
        <lem>-saṁp<choice><sic>r̥</sic><corr>rī</corr></choice>tair</lem>
        <note>As Chhabra points out, <foreign>saṁpr̥ta</foreign> could be derived from the verb <foreign>pr̥ṇoti</foreign>, but this is restricted to Vedic usage and thus the intent here must have been <foreign>saṁprīta</foreign>.</note>
      </app>
      <app loc="26">
        <lem>-sīmaiva<g type="commaHigh">.</g></lem>
        <note>I follow Chhabra's edition, which prints an original punctuation mark here. In the estampage, only a space is visible.</note>
      </app>




   </listApp>
  </div>

</div>



<div type="translation" resp="part:daba">
  <note type="credit">For the Telugu words and passage in this inscription, I rely on Chhabra's translation, who in turn had received language help from N. Laksminarayan Rao (and, apparently, from C. R. Krishnamacharlu).</note>
  <div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
<p n="1-16">Greetings. The grandson of King <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>bhūpāla</foreign></supplied> Cālukya-Bhīma, whose pair of lotus feet were engilded by a mass of beams from gems fitted to the surfaces of the crowns of enemy kings bowed down by the blade of his sword and who was like forehead mark on the dynasty of Satyāśraya Vallabhendra <supplied reason="explanation">Pulakeśin II</supplied>, who was eager to adorn  the lineage of the majestic Caḷukyas—who are of the Mānavya <foreign>gotra</foreign> which is praised by the entire world, who are sons of Hārīti, who attained kingship by the grace of Kauśikī’s boon,<note>Or, alternatively, by the grace of Kauśikī’s bridegroom, i.e. Śiva. In spite of its slight awkwardness, I prefer the former interpretation because the Bādāmi Cālukyas refer to themselves as nourished <foreign>saṁvardhita</foreign> by Kauśikī.</note> who are protected by the band of Mothers, who were deliberately appointed <supplied reason="explanation">to kingship</supplied> by Lord Mahāsena, to whom the realms of adversaries instantaneously submit at the <supplied reason="subaudible">mere</supplied> sight of the superior Boar emblem they have acquired by the grace of the divine Nārāyaṇa, and whose bodies have been hallowed through washing in the purificatory ablutions <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>avabhr̥tha</foreign></supplied> of the Aśvamedha sacrifice—; the son of Vijayāditya <supplied reason="explanation">IV</supplied>, the shelter of the entire universe <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>samasta-bhuvanāśraya</foreign></supplied> who was a wish-fulfilling tree to the class of Brahmins whom he endowed with that special great gift <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>mahā-dāna</foreign></supplied> that is a pile of gleaming gold whose great weight has been weighed in the balance against his own body <supplied reason="subaudible">girt</supplied> with sword and armour: King <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>mahīpati</foreign></supplied> Amma <supplied reason="explanation">I</supplied> Gaṇḍaragaṇḍa, widely known as Rājamahendra, the shelter of all the world <supplied reason="explanation">sarva-lokāśraya</supplied>, His Majesty Viṣṇuvardhana <supplied reason="explanation">VI</supplied> the Supreme Lord <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>parameśvara</foreign></supplied> of Emperors <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>mahārājādhirāja</foreign></supplied>, the Supreme Sovereign <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>parama-bhaṭṭāraka</foreign></supplied>, supreme devotee of Maheśvara, whose right arm is complemented with a gleaming sword that is like a ray of the sun rising against the darkness consisting of his rivals, convokes and commands the householders <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>kuṭumbin</foreign></supplied>—including foremost the territorial overseers <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>rāṣṭrakūṭa</foreign></supplied>—who reside in Gudravāra district <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>viṣaya</foreign></supplied> as follows:</p>
<p n="16-25">Let it be known to you <supplied reason="subaudible">that</supplied> the grandson of Candeyarāja of the Kona family, who had achieved the exaltation of <supplied reason="subaudible">becoming</supplied> the overseer <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>rāṣṭrakūṭa</foreign></supplied> of the magnificent village named Umikili in Gudravāra district and who ascended an elephant as a favour of King <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>mahārāja</foreign></supplied> Vijayāditya <supplied reason="explanation">III</supplied> who was called Guṇakkenalla, the son of Manohitārya who was the younger brother of Rājāditya, the good soldier named Vemarāja who by his daring is a Śūdraka of the Kali age, has sought the favour of my father Vijayāditya <supplied reason="explanation">IV</supplied>, taking on a <foreign>karpaṭaka</foreign> <supplied reason="explanation">vow</supplied><note>Literally, a vow of wearing rags. See the commentary.</note> in his devotion to his lord. Being pleased with his worship and devotion to his lord, on the occasion of the <foreign>anna-prāśana</foreign> of Prince Vijayāditya <supplied reason="explanation">V</supplied> we have made that Vemarāja the headman <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>grāmaṇī</foreign></supplied> of Umikilī village, exempt from all taxes except for the traditional dues of cultivated land <supplied reason="subaudible">which are set at</supplied> eight <foreign>gadyāṇaka</foreign>s.<note>Chhabra understands the text to mean that Vemarāja was raised to headman by this grant, and was, incidentally as it were, granted a tax exemption. This does not seem so certain to me; the charter may well mean that he was already headman by heredity, and the object of the grant is only the exemption, which may in turn be limited to the two fields specified below. A note in Chhabra’s edition (<bibl><ref target="bib:Chhabra1947-1948_02"/><citedRange unit="page">43</citedRange><citedRange unit="note">2</citedRange></bibl>), signed C. R. K. and probably added by C. R. Krishnamacharlu, points out that the donation may have been comprised only of these two fields.</note></p>
<p n="25-27">To the south of the village is the <foreign>ervvoka</foreign> field <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>cenu</foreign></supplied>.<note>In the this paragraph and the next, I follow Chhabra in the translation of the Telugu words. Chhabra further notes that according to C. R. Krishnamacharlu, <foreign>ervvoka</foreign> may be connected to the Telugu word <foreign>eruvāka</foreign>.</note> Its boundaries <supplied reason="subaudible">are as follows</supplied>. To the east, a marshy pool <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>vranta</foreign></supplied>. To the south, the perimeter of Dūdrupāka itself. To the west, the king’s field <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>rāca-cenu</foreign></supplied> and the field of the Cāṇḍālas. To the north, a stream <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>koḍu</foreign></supplied>.<note>Translating <foreign>koḍu</foreign> as “brook,” Chhabra refers to Kielhorn (<bibl rend="omitname"><ref target="bib:Kielhorn1898-1899_01"/><citedRange unit="page">139</citedRange></bibl>), who in turn refers to Campbell’s <title>Teloogoo Dictionary</title> which translates this word as <q>a rivulet, the branch of a river</q>.</note></p>
<p n="27-29">In the northern direction of the village is the Ervvoka field <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>cenu</foreign></supplied> of Aypa/).<note>According to Chhabra, Aypa is to be understood as Ayyapa.</note> Its boundaries <supplied reason="subaudible">are as follows</supplied>. To the east, a stream <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>koḍu</foreign></supplied>. To the south, the Vanneṟu<note>According to Chhabra, this is the name of a river. If this is correct, then this river, major enough to have a name of its own, separated the field from the village to which it belonged.</note> To the south, a stream <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>koḍu</foreign></supplied>. To the north, the landing to the lake <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>kolani mulugu</foreign></supplied>.<note>Chhabra: <q>the bathing place at the lake (@or the drain from the lake@)</q>.</note></p>
<p n="29-30">The arrangement <supplied reason="explanation">for the remuneration which he is to receive</supplied> in grain measures <supplied reason="explanation">i.e. in kind</supplied> is as follows: the income of <foreign>saveram</foreign> is ten <foreign>kaṇḍu</foreign>s and seventeen <foreign>tūmu</foreign>s <supplied reason="explanation">measured by measure</supplied> of 24 full <foreign>puṭṭi</foreign>s; of <foreign>tammulam</foreign>, one <foreign>tūmu</foreign>.<note>The translation of this Telugu passage has been adopted literally from Chhabra.</note></p>
<p n="30-32">Let no-one pose an obstacle <supplied reason="explanation">to his enjoyment of his rights</supplied> over it. He who does so shall be conjoined with the five great sins. So too Vyāsa has said:</p>
<p rend="stanza" n="1">Many <supplied reason="explanation">kings</supplied> have granted land, and many have preserved it <supplied reason="explanation">as formerly granted</supplied>. Whosoever at any time owns the land, the fruit {reward <supplied reason="explanation">accrued of granting it</supplied>} belongs to him at that time.</p>
<p rend="stanza" n="2">He who would seize land, whether given by himself or by another, shall be born as a worm in faeces for sixty thousand years.</p>
<p rend="stanza" n="3">The executor <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>samājñapti</foreign></supplied> is the castellan <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>kaṭakeśvara</foreign></supplied><note>The term <foreign>kaṭakeśvara</foreign> was probably used here instead of the more common <foreign>kaṭaka-rāja</foreign> or its vernacular variant <foreign>kaḍa-eṟeya</foreign> for metrical reasons, as pointed out by Chhabra. These terms are normally understood to mean a chief officer of the royal camp (cf. <bibl><ptr target="bib:Fleet1902-1903_01"/><citedRange>183-185</citedRange></bibl> and <bibl><ptr target="bib:Sircar1966_01"/><citedRange unit="entry">kaṭaka-rāja</citedRange></bibl>). However, as it seems to denote a very high hereditary office in the Cālukyan court, I believe it had in this case no direct association with any army camps.</note> the power of whose arms is the protection of the territory of Veṅgī. <supplied reason="subaudible">This charter was</supplied> composed by Bhaṭṭa Mahākāla, progeny of Bhaṭṭa Niravadya.<note>The castellan may be the same person as Bhaṭṭa Mahākāla; at any rate, the descendants of Bhaṭṭa Niravadya did normally serve in that function. The text, however, does not indicate in any way that the two are one.</note></p>
<p n="47"/>
  </div>
</div>



<div type="translation" xml:lang="fra" source="bib:Estienne-Monod2008_01">
  <div type="textpart" n="A"><head xml:lang="eng">Seal</head>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" n="B"><head xml:lang="eng">Plates</head>
<p n="1-16">Prospérité ! le petit-fils du roi Cālukya Bhīma, dont les pieds de lotus sont rougis par des multitudes de rayons des pierres précieuses serties sur l’orbe des diadèmes des rois ennemis, soumis par la lame de son épée, devenue le joyau de la lignée de Satyāśraya Vallabhendra, ornement de la lignée des Calukya, illustres, du même <foreign>gotra</foreign> que les descendants de Manu, honorés dans l’univers entier, fils de Hāritī, qui obtinrent leur royaume grâce à l’excellente faveur de Kauśikī, protégés par la troupes des Mères, méditant aux pieds du seigneur Mahāsena, dont le cercle des ennemis fut soumis en un instant à la vue du signe illustre de l’excellent sanglier, faveur octroyée par le bienheureux Nārāyaṇa, dont les corps furent purifiés par le bain purificatoire de l’aśvamedha, fils de Vijayāditya, arbre à vœux pour des multitudes de brahmanes, qu’il rendit exceptionnellement riches avec le grand don d’une immense quantité d’or lumineux, dont le poids immense avait été pesé sur la balance au moyen de son propre corps, ceint de son épée, refuge de l’univers entier, le roi Amma, renommé sous le titre de Gaṇḍara-Gaṇḍo Rājamahendra, dont le bras droit était armé d’une lumineuse épée dardant des rayons, soleil se levant sur les ténèbres de ses rivaux, refuge de tous les hommes, l’illustre Viṣṇuvardhana, roi suprême des souverains de grands rois, éminent seigneur, excellent dévôt de Māheśvara, ordonne ceci aux chefs de famille rassemblés, habitants le <foreign>viṣaya</foreign> de Gudravāra, <foreign>rāṣṭrakūṭa</foreign> en tête :</p>
<p n="16-25">qu’il soit connu de vous que le petit-fils de Konakula Candeyarāja qui acquit la distinction <supplied reason="subaudible">d’être</supplied> <foreign>rāṣṭrakūṭa</foreign> du village illustre nommé Umikili, dans le <foreign>viṣaya</foreign> de Gudravāra, qui obtint de monter sur un éléphant par la faveur octroyée par le grand roi Vijayāditya, nommé aussi Guṇakkenalla, fils du frère cadet de Rājāditya, Manohitārya, <supplied reason="subaudible">lui qui est </supplied> nommé Vemarāja, bon guerrier, Śudraka du Kaliyuga par son audace, a donné satisfaction à mon père Vijayāditya, vêtu de haillons, dévoué à son seigneur. Par nous, satisfaits par sa dévotion envers son seigneur et par ses hommages, à l’occasion de l’<foreign>annaprāśana</foreign><note>Rite célébrant la première nourriture de riz donnée à un enfant.</note> du prince Vijayāditya, exempté <supplied reason="subaudible">de taxe</supplied>, excepté celle des huit <foreign>gadyāṇaka</foreign><note>Nom d’une valeur monétaire, D. C. Sircar, 1966, p. 432.</note> qui constituent le revenu fixe,<note>ibid., p. 311.</note> perçu selon la tradition, Vemarāja est nommé chef de village<note>grāmaṇī est un équivalent de grāmakuṭa, ibid., p.121.</note> du village d’Umikilī.</p>
<p n="25-27">Au sud du village <supplied reason="subaudible">se trouve</supplied> le terrain d’Ervvoka.<note>Traduction de l’éditeur.</note>
Ses limites sont :
à l’est un marécage,<note>Traduction de l’éditeur.</note>
au sud la limite précise de Dūdrupāka,
à l’ouest le terrain royal<note>Traduction de l’éditeur.</note> et le terrain des Cāṇḍāla,
au nord un ruisseau.<note>Selon le Campbell’s teloogoo dictionary, koḍu désigne un ruisseau ; en kannara le même mot désigne le sommet d’une colline. Indication de l’éditeur n. 3 p.47, renvoi à Ep. Ind., V, p. 139, n.2.</note></p>
<p n="27-29">Au nord du village <supplied reason="subaudible">se trouve</supplied> le terrain Ervvoka appartenant à Ayyapa.<note>Traduction de l’éditeur.</note>
Les limites de ce dernier sont :
à l’est un ruisseau.
au sud Vanneṟu,<note>Nom d’une rivière.</note>
à l’ouest un ruisseau,
au nord un canal venant du lac,<note>Traduction de l’éditeur.</note></p>
<p n="29-30">L’arrangement <supplied reason="subaudible">pour la rémunération qu’il recevra</supplied> en mesure de grains est le suivant : un revenu de saveram ? de dix kaṇḍu et dix-sept tūmu mesuré selon la mesure de vingt-quatre puṭṭi, de tammulam ? un tūmu.<note>Passage en telugu, nous n’avons pu définir le sens de certains termes, que nous avons restitués tels qu’ils étaient indiqués dans le texte. L’éditeur ne propose pas non plus de traduction pour ces mots.</note>
</p>
<p n="30-32">Aucune charge ne doit lui être imposée, celui qui en impose est lié aux cinq grands crimes. Ainsi Vyāsa a dit :</p>
<p rend="stanza" n="1">Beaucoup ont donné une terre, beaucoup l’ont protégée,
celui qui possède la terre en possède la fruit.</p>
<p rend="stanza" n="2">Qu’elle soit donnée par lui ou par un autre, celui qui prend une terre
renaît ver de terre dans les excréments pendant soixante mille ans.</p>
<p rend="stanza" n="3">Le <foreign>kaṭakeśvara</foreign>, dont la puissance du bras protège le royaume de Veṁgī, est l’exécuteur.
<supplied reason="subaudible">Cet édit</supplied> a été composé par l’éminent Mahākāla, descendant de l’éminent Niravadya.
</p>
  </div>
</div>




<div type="commentary">
<p>Discovered in Cēvūru village in Kaikalūr tāluk of Kistna District in the Madras Presidency, about 1928, by the villager Polavarapu Ankayya, son of Venkata Reddi, who was digging the debris of a collapsed mud house. Seen there by Chhabra in November 1938 and borrowed for study.</p>
<p>More detail about the term <foreign>karpaṭa</foreign> is found in the <ref target="DHARMA_INSVengiCalukya00039.xml">Māṁgallu gramt of Dānārṇava</ref>. There it is not a military man but a scholar who undertakes <foreign>karpaṭa</foreign> for the sake of the <foreign>rāṣṭrakūṭa</foreign> Kākaṭya Guṇḍyana in order to secure his favour (ll50-52, <foreign>guṇḍyanaṁ vīram uddiśya … yena karppaṭam ābaddhaṁ tat-prasādābhikāṁkṣiṇā</foreign>). The chief in turn grants him a village. This vow (l53, <foreign>karppaṭī-vrata</foreign>) is said there to involve morning baths and chastity, but the wearing of rags is not explicitly mentioned. I assume that this vow was performed with the declared intent that the merit thereby acquired go to the performer's metaphysical stockpile, that it was at the time an established method of acquiring a land grant and/or the position of headman for the performer or his descendants, and that in the present case Vemarāja performed it after retiring from the military. It is also possible that, both here and there, the word is used figuratively in the sense of utterly selfless service.</p>
<p>As Chhabra points out, the last stanza lacks one mora at the end. He suggests <foreign>-bhaṭṭa-mahākāla idam akarot</foreign>. Though metrically correct and appropriate to the context, my preference would be <foreign>-bhaṭṭa-mahākāla-racitam idaṁ</foreign>.</p>
</div>



<div type="bibliography">
  <p>Edited from the original by B. Ch. Chhabra (<bibl rend="omitname"><ptr target="bib:Chhabra1947-1948_02"/></bibl>), with translation and inked rubbings supplied by Hultzsch. The present edition by Dániel Balogh is based on a collation of Chhabra's text with his facsimiles.</p>
  <listBibl type="primary">
    <bibl n="BCC"><ptr target="bib:Chhabra1947-1948_02"/></bibl><!-- one <bibl/> per item of primary bibliography -->
  </listBibl>
  <listBibl type="secondary">
    <bibl/>
  </listBibl>
</div>



    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
