<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Mēlappaḻuvūr, *** temple, time of ***, year **</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:vagi">
 <forename>Valérie</forename>
						<surname>Gillet</surname>
 </persName>
 <persName ref="part:emfr">
 	<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
 <surname>Francis</surname>
 </persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSMelKil00121</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary><p>#121. a) Tiruvālantuṟai Mahādeva temple, inner compound wall; b) on the southern outer face of the compound wall; c) personally located and read in situ; d) ARE 1926, no. 257; e) 11th regnal year and 284 days of Tribhuvana Cakkaravattikaḷ Śrī Rājādhirājadevar Tribhuvana Cakkaravatti Kōṉerinmai Koṇṭāṉ; f) Rājādhirāja I or II; g) inscription read with G. Vijayavenugopal; this unpublished inscription was difficult to decipher and understand and I could not have done it without his help and explanations.</p>

</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-06-10" status="draft">Conversion to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <hi rend="grantha">tribhu</hi>vanac cakkaravattikaḷ <hi rend="grantha">śrī</hi> rā<hi rend="grantha">jādh</hi>[<hi rend="grantha">i</hi>]rā<hi rend="grantha">jade</hi>vaṟku yāṇṭu patinoṉṟu nāḷ Irunūṟṟeṇpattuṉāli nāl <hi rend="grantha">tribhu</hi>vanac cakkaravatti koṉerinmai koṇṭān kunṟakkūṟṟamāna Ut
<lb n="2"/>tuṅkatuṅkavaḷanāṭṭut tiṟappum tevatānamum Iruppakārattukku Aṭaitta Ūrkaḷumuḷḷiṭṭa Ūrkaḷilāṟku Innāṭṭurkūḷap aṭaip paṟṟāyk kāṇiyāḷar payiṟ ceytu vārāmaiyil pattāva
<lb n="3"/>tu mutal kāṇiyāḷare payiṟ ceytu kaṭamaiy iṟuttu varukiṟa naṉcey nilattil veli monṉrukku ˚ eṇpatin kalamum Eṇpatin kalattukku meṟpaṭavum koṇṭu varukiṟa Ūrkaḷ Eṇpatin kalam āka [Am] Aṟupatin kala
<lb n="4"/>mum aṟupatiṉ kalattukku meṟpaṭavuṅ koṇṭu varukiṟa Ūrkaḷ Aṟupatin kalam ākavum nāṟpatin malamum nāṟpatin kalattukku meṟpaṭavuṅ koṇṭu varukiṟa Ūrkaḷ nāṟpatin kalam ākavum [A]nnel Oṭṭāka mutal
<lb n="5"/>koḷḷavum Iṉnel naṭṭan[i]laṅkaṉ munpu koṇṭu varukiṟa paṭaye Ivvar caikku Onṟu mukkālāka Iṟukkavum putitākak kuḷaṅ kallit tiruttip payiṟ ceyta nilaṅkaḷukku Iṉnel varicaip paṭiye mutal koṇṭu tiruttina [Ā]
<lb n="6"/>[Ā]ṇṭu Iṟaiyiliyāy Itan Etirāmāṇṭu Onṟu kuralūm Itan Etirāmāṇṭu Onṟupātiyum Itan Etirāmāṇṭu Onṟu mukkālum Itan Etirāmāṇṭu mutal nirampavum Iṟukkappeṟayeṇumenṟu pallavarā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>n namakkuc conna <gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/> 
<lb n="7"/>[yi]l Ippaṭi ceyyakkaṭava[t]ākac collik kaṇakkilum Iṭṭuk koḷḷakkaṭavarkaḷukka varikkū[ṟu] ceyvārkaḷukkum conṉom Innāṭṭurkaḷukku pattāvatu mutal Ippaṭiyāl [ve]nta kaṭamai Iṟukka Eḻutinān tirumantira Olai neṟi Uṭaiccoḻamu
<lb n="8"/>ventaveḷān [E]ḻuttiṭṭār nilakaṅkaraiyar vāṇātāra[yar] nantipanmar malaiyappiyārayar kanakaracāttipattaraicar villavarācar
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Gillet2024_01">

<p>Fortune! Prosperity! This is the eleventh year and two hundred and eighty-four days of Tribhuvana Cakkaravattikaḷ Śrī Rājādhirājadevar, Tribhuvana Cakkaravatti Kōṉeriṉmai Koṇṭāṉ. The lessees (<foreign>kāṇiyāḷar</foreign>) having cultivated (<foreign>payiṟ ceytu</foreign>) as land (<foreign>paṟṟāy</foreign>) joining (<foreign>aṭai</foreign>) the village tank (<foreign>urkūḷap</foreign> &gt; <foreign>ūrkuḷam</foreign>) of this <foreign>nāṭu</foreign> (<foreign>ināṭṭu</foreign>), for those in the villages (<foreign>ūrkaḷilāṟku</foreign>) including (<foreign>uḷḷiṭṭa</foreign>) all the villages (<foreign>ūrkaḷum</foreign>) assigned (<foreign>aṭaitta</foreign>) to the Brahmin residence (<foreign>iruppu-akarāttu</foreign>), the <foreign>devadāna</foreign>, and the assessed lands (<foreign>tiṟappum</foreign>) of Uttuṅkatuṅkavaḷanāṭu alias Kuṉṟakkūṟṟam (<foreign>kunṟakkūṟṟam</foreign> &gt; <foreign>kuṉṟakkūṟṟam</foreign>); if it is not coming (<foreign>vārāmaiyil</foreign>) from (<foreign>mutal</foreign>) the tenth year (<foreign>pattāvatu</foreign>), the lessees themselves (<foreign>kāṇiyāḷarē</foreign>) having cultivated (<foreign>payiṟ ceytu</foreign>), in the wet land (<foreign>naṉcey nilattil</foreign>) which has come (<foreign>varukiṟa</foreign>), having paid (<foreign>iṟuttu</foreign>) the <foreign>kaṭamai</foreign>-tax: for one (<foreign>monṟukku</foreign> &gt; <foreign>oṉṟukku</foreign>) <foreign>vēli</foreign>, as eighty (<foreign>eṇpatin</foreign>) <foreign>kalam</foreign>s for the villages (<foreign>ūrkaḷ</foreign>) which have come (<foreign>varukiṟa</foreign>), with (<foreign>koṇṭu</foreign>) an excess (<foreign>mēṟpaṭavuṅ</foreign>) [above] eighty <foreign>kalam</foreign>s (<foreign>eṇpatin kalattukku</foreign>), [this is] eighty <foreign>kalam</foreign>s (<foreign>eṇpatin kalamum</foreign>); this has to be (<foreign>ākavum</foreign>) sixty (<foreign>aṟupatin</foreign>) for the villages (<foreign>ūrkaḷ</foreign>) which have come (<foreign>varukiṟa</foreign>) with (<foreign>koṇṭu</foreign>) an excess (<foreign>mēṟpaṭavuṅ</foreign>) [above] sixty <foreign>kalam</foreign>s (<foreign>aṟupatiṉ kalattukku</foreign>), [this is] sixty <foreign>kalam</foreign>s (<foreign>aṟupatiṉ kalamum</foreign>); this has to be (<foreign>ākavum</foreign>) fourty (<foreign>nāṟpatin</foreign>) for the villages (<foreign>ūrkaḷ</foreign>) which have come (<foreign>varukiṟa</foreign>) with (<foreign>koṇṭu</foreign>) an excess (<foreign>mēṟpaṭavuṅ</foreign>) [above] fourty <foreign>kalam</foreign>s (<foreign>nāṟpatin kalattukku</foreign>), [this is] fourty <foreign>kalam</foreign>s (<foreign>nāṟpatin malamum</foreign>&gt; <foreign>kalamum</foreign>); that paddy (<foreign>annel</foreign>) that we will get (<foreign>koḷḷavum</foreign>) as capital (<foreign>mutal</foreign>) all together (<foreign>oṭṭu-āka</foreign>), we will have to pay (<foreign>iṟukkavum</foreign>) as (<foreign>āka</foreign>) one (<foreign>oṉṟu</foreign>) three quarter (<foreign>mukkāl</foreign>) for a <foreign>cey</foreign> (<foreign>caikku</foreign> &gt; <foreign>ceykku</foreign>) of those (<foreign>ivvar</foreign>); that is the order (<foreign>paṭayē</foreign> &gt; <foreign>paṭiyē</foreign>) which has come (<foreign>varukiṟa</foreign>) with (<foreign>koṇṭu</foreign>) the previous (<foreign>munpu</foreign>) lands (<foreign>nilaṅkaḷ</foreign>) established (<foreign>naṭṭa</foreign>) with this paddy (<foreign>iṉnel</foreign>); having newly (<foreign>putitāka</foreign>) dug (<foreign>kalli</foreign>) the tank (<foreign>kuḷaṅ</foreign>), having revovated [it] (<foreign>tirutti</foreign>), having improved (<foreign>tirutti</foreign>) with (<foreign>koṇṭu</foreign>) the capital (<foreign>mutal</foreign>) [as per] the order (<foreign>paṭiyē</foreign>) for the tax (<foreign>varicai</foreign>) on this paddy (<foreign>iṉnel</foreign>), having become without tax (<foreign>iṟaiyiliyāy</foreign>) [in that] year (<foreign>āṇṭu</foreign>); in the year opposite this one (<foreign>itaṉ etirāmaṇṭu</foreign>), one quarter (<foreign>oṉṟu kuralūm</foreign> &gt; <foreign>oṉṟu kālum</foreign>); in the year opposite this one (<foreign>itaṉ etirāmaṇṭu</foreign>), one half (<foreign>oṉṟu pāṭiyum</foreign>); in the year opposite this one (<foreign>itaṉ etirāmaṇṭu</foreign>), one three quarters (<foreign>onṟu mukkālum</foreign>); in the year opposite this one (<foreign>itaṉ etirāmaṇṭu</foreign>), the full (<foreign>nirampavum</foreign>) capital (<foreign>mutal</foreign>), Pallavarājan said (<foreign>eṉṟu</foreign>): “it has to be (<foreign>peṟaveṇum</foreign> &gt; <foreign>peṟa-veṇṭum</foreign>) paid (<foreign>iṟukka</foreign>)”; since he said (<foreign>conna</foreign>{{<foreign>mai</foreign>}}<foreign>yil</foreign>) to us (<foreign>namakku</foreign>), having said (<foreign>colli</foreign>) that which has to be done (<foreign>ceyyakkaṭavatāka</foreign>) in this manner (<foreign>ippaṭi</foreign>), we say (<foreign>conṉōm</foreign> &gt; <foreign>coṉṉōm</foreign>) to those who have to take (<foreign>koḷḷakkaṭavarkaḷukka</foreign> &gt; <foreign>koḷḷakkaṭavarkaḷukku</foreign>) having put (<foreign>iṭṭu</foreign>) in the account book (<foreign>kaṇakkilum</foreign>) and to those who apportion taxes (<foreign>varikkūṟu ceyvārkaḷukkum</foreign>); from (<foreign>mutal</foreign>) the tenth year (<foreign>pattāvatu</foreign>), to the villages of this <foreign>nāṭu</foreign> (<foreign>innāṭṭūrkaḷukku</foreign>), to pay (<foreign>iṟukka</foreign>) the <foreign>kaṭamai</foreign>-tax which came (<foreign>venta</foreign> &gt; <foreign>vanta</foreign>) with this order (<foreign>ippaṭiyāl</foreign>), Neṟi Uṭaiccōḻamūventavēḷān wrote (<foreign>eḻutiṉān</foreign>) the palm-leaf royal order (<foreign>tirumantira ōlai</foreign>). Those who signed (<foreign>eḻuttiṭṭār</foreign>) [are] Nilakaṅkaraiyar, Vāṇātārayar, Nantipanmar, Malaiyappiyārayar, Kanakaracāttipattaraicar, Villavarācar.</p></div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

 <p>Reported in <bibl><ptr target="bib:ARIE1923-1924"/></bibl> (ARIE/1923-1924/C/1924/***).</p>
 <p>Edited and translated in <bibl><ptr target="bib:Gillet2024_01"/></bibl>, based on autopsy and photographs (<ref target="https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/****">by Valérie Gillet, 2016-2018</ref>).</p>
 <p>This digital edition by Valérie Gillet and Emmanuel Francis.</p>

 <listBibl type="primary">
 <bibl>
 <ptr target="bib:Gillet2024_01"/>
 <citedRange unit="page">TBC</citedRange>
 <citedRange unit="item">TBC</citedRange>
 </bibl>
 </listBibl>

 <listBibl type="secondary">
 <bibl>
 <ptr target="bib:ARIE1923-1924"/>
 <citedRange unit="page">TBC</citedRange>
 <citedRange unit="appendix">C/1924</citedRange>
 <citedRange unit="item">TBC</citedRange>
 </bibl>

 </listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
