<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Mēlappaḻuvūr, *** temple, time of ***, year **</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:vagi">
 <forename>Valérie</forename>
						<surname>Gillet</surname>
 </persName>
 <persName ref="part:emfr">
 	<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
 <surname>Francis</surname>
 </persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSMelKil00131</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary><p>#131. a) Tiruvālantuṟai Mahādeva temple, inner compound wall; b) on the western outer face of the compound wall, in the group of inscriptions; c) personally located and read in situ; d) ARE 1895, no. 105; SII 5, no. 666; SII 3, part II, no. 71 (edition and translation); e) 20th regnal year of Kōrājakesarivarman Tiripuvaṉa Cakkaravattikaḷ Śrī Kolottuṅkacōḻatēvar; f) Kulottuṅga I (<foreign>circa</foreign> 1089 A.D.); g) lines 18 and 19 only read with G. Vijayavenugopal; h) lines 1 to 17 contain the <foreign>meykkīrtti</foreign> of Kulottuṅga I.</p>

</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-06-10" status="draft">Conversion to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1–16"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī </hi>{<hi rend="grantha">meykkīrtti</hi>}
<lb n="17"/>{<hi rend="grantha">meykkīrtti</hi>} korā<hi rend="grantha">ja</hi>kecariva<hi rend="grantha">nma</hi>rāna tiripuvaṉac cakkaravattikaḷ <hi rend="grantha">śrī </hi>kolottuṅkacoḻatevarkku yāṇṭu irupatāva
<lb n="18"/>tu Uttoṅkatoṅkavaḷanāṭṭuk kunṟakkūṟṟattu<hi rend="grantha">brahma</hi>teyam ciṟupaḻuvūr [<hi rend="grantha">sa</hi>]<hi rend="grantha">bhai</hi>yom vitarā<hi rend="grantha">ja </hi>payaṅkara vāṇakovaraiyar taṅkaḷḷācci coḻakula cuntaran viccā
<lb n="19"/>tiriyāḻvārkku<hi rend="grantha">sabhai </hi>vilaiyāka viṟṟuk kuṭutta nilamāvatu rā<hi rend="grantha">jentra</hi>coḻavākkālukku vaṭakku pavitti[ra]māṇikka vatikkuk kiḻakku mutal kaṇṇāṟṟu Iraṇ
<lb n="20"/>ṭām caturattu nilam nālumāvil vaṭakaṭaiy nilam Orumāvil kiḻkkaṭay nilam Ar[ai]māvum Ivvatikkuk kiḻakku Ivvākkālukku vaṭakku Iraṇṭāṅ ka
<lb n="21"/>ṇṇāṟṟu Iraṇṭāñ catiram nilam nālumāvil vaṭakkaṭaiy nilam Orumāvil meṟkkaṭaiy nilam Araimāvum Āka nilam Oru mā Innilam Orumāvum Ivaru
<lb n="22"/>kku viṟṟuk koḷvatāna Emmill icaiñca vilaipporuḷ Anṟāāṭu ṉalkkācu Onṟu Ikkācu Onṟum Āvaṇakkaḷiye kaiccellaṟak koṇṭu viṟṟu vilaiyā
<lb n="23"/>vaṇam ceyitu kuṭuttom<hi rend="grantha">bra</hi>[<hi rend="grantha">hma</hi>]teyam ciṟupaḻuvūr <hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>yom Innilam Orumāvukkum Ituve vi[l]aiyolai Āvatākavum Ituve porumāvaṟu
<lb n="24"/>tip poruḷ cilavolai yāvatākavum Ituvalatu veṟu porumāvaṟtip poruḷc cilavolai kāṭṭakkaṭavar Allātārākavum Ippaṭi Icaiñ
<lb n="25"/>cu ˚ ikkācu Onṟum koṇ]ṭu Innilam Orumāvum vilaikkaṟa viṟṟu poruḷ aṟak koṇṭom ciṟupaḻuvūr<hi rend="grantha">sabhai</hi>yom Ivarkaḷ paṇikka Ippiramāṇam Eḻuti[ne]
<lb n="26"/>[n] [<hi rend="grantha">ma</hi>]<hi rend="grantha">dhyasta</hi>n paḻuvūr uṭaiyān Ā[yi]rattirun[ū]ṟṟuvan muṭikoṇṭānen Ivai Enneḻut[tu] Ippaṭikk[u c]ānta maṅkalattu [pālā]ciriyan [I]lakkuvaṇaṉ
<lb n="27"/><note>SII reads<hi rend="grantha">kūttapp</hi> before the <hi rend="grantha">nnen</hi>, but I cannot locate it on the stone. From this line, the inscription is inscribed on the ledge at the bottom of the wall.</note>nnen Ivai enneḻuttu Ippaṭikku paḻuvū cavānti nārāṇanen Ivai Enneḻuttu Itu cānti palāciriyan viranārāyaṇantu Itu cāvānti nārāyaṇan māṟan
<lb n="28"/>[pu]<hi rend="grantha">syaiñai</hi> yippaṭi Aṟiven Ivvūr viracoḻa viṇṇakārāḻvār koyil tiruvārātane paṇṇum nārāyaṇan tiruvāyikkulam uṭaiyānen Ippaṭi Aṟiven
<lb n="29"/>Ivvūr [ka]ruma[ka]n Itu pa<hi rend="grantha">mā</hi>[<hi rend="grantha">he</hi>]<hi rend="grantha">śva</hi>[[<hi rend="grantha">ra ra</hi>]]<hi rend="grantha">kṣai </hi>||
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Gillet2024_01">

<p>Fortune! Prosperity! {<foreign>meykkīrtti</foreign>} This is the twentieth year of Kōrājakesarivarman alias Tiripuvaṉa Cakkaravattikaḷ Śrī Kolottuṅkacōḻatēvar. We the Sabhā of Ciṟupaḻuvūr, a <foreign>brahmadeya</foreign> of Kuṉṟakkūṟṟam [alias] Uttuṅkatuṅkavaḷanāṭu; for Cuntaran Viccātiriyāḻvār of the Cōḻa line (<foreign>kula</foreign>), our (<foreign>taṅkaḷ</foreign>) mother (<foreign>ācci</foreign>) of Vitarāja Payaṅkara Vāṇakōvaraiyar, the Sabhā, having sold (<foreign>viṟṟu</foreign>) for a price (<foreign>vilaiyāka</foreign>) gave (<foreign>kuṭutta</foreign>) the following land (<foreign>nilamāvatu</foreign>): to the north (<foreign>vaṭakku</foreign>) of the Rājendracōḻa canal (<foreign>vākkālukku</foreign> &gt; <foreign>vāykkālukku</foreign>), to the east (<foreign>kīḻakku</foreign>) of the Pavittramāṇikka channel (<foreign>vatikku</foreign>), the northern boundary (<foreign>vaṭakaṭai</foreign>) [is] in the four <foreign>mā</foreign>s (<foreign>nālumāvil</foreign>) of land (<foreign>nilam</foreign>) of the two (<foreign>iraṇṭām</foreign>) squares (<foreign>caturattu</foreign>) of the first (<foreign>mutal</foreign>) canal (<foreign>kaṇṇāṟṟu</foreign>); the eastern boundary (<foreign>kīḻkkaṭai</foreign>) [is] in the one <foreign>mā</foreign> (<foreign>orumāvil</foreign>) of land (<foreign>nilam</foreign>); the northern boundary (<foreign>vaṭakaṭai</foreign>) [is] in four <foreign>mā</foreign>s (<foreign>nālumāvil</foreign>) of land (<foreign>nilam</foreign>) of the two squares (<foreign>iraṇṭāñ catiram</foreign> &gt; <foreign>caturam</foreign>) and the two channels (<foreign>iraṇṭāṅ kaṇṇāṟṟu</foreign>) to the north (<foreign>vaṭakku</foreign>) of this canal (<foreign>ivvākālukku</foreign>) and to the east (<foreign>kīḻakku</foreign>) of this channel (<foreign>ivvatikku</foreign>) and a fourtieth (<foreign>araimāvum</foreign>) of land (<foreign>nilam</foreign>); the western boundary (<foreign>mēṟkkaṭai</foreign>) [is] in one <foreign>mā</foreign> (<foreign>orumāvil</foreign>) of land (<foreign>nilam</foreign>); one <foreign>mā </foreign>of land (<foreign>nilam oru mā</foreign>) as a fourtieth (<foreign>araimāvum</foreign>) of land (<foreign>nilam</foreign>); having sold (<foreign>viṟṟu</foreign>) to him (<foreign>ivarukku</foreign>) one <foreign>mā</foreign> (<foreign>orumāvum</foreign>) of this land (<foreign>innilam</foreign>), we have to get (<foreign>koḷvatāna</foreign>) the sale price (<foreign>vilaipporuḷ</foreign>) agreed (<foreign>icaiñca</foreign> &gt; <foreign>icainta</foreign>) among us (<foreign>emmil</foreign>) of one (<foreign>oṉṟu</foreign>) good <foreign>kācu</foreign> (<foreign>ṉalkkācu </foreign>&gt; <foreign>nalkkācu</foreign>) of the time (<foreign>anṟāāṭu</foreign> &gt; <foreign>aṉṟāṭu</foreign>); this one <foreign>kācu</foreign> (<foreign>ikkācu oṉṟum</foreign>), having taken (<foreign>koṇṭu</foreign>) completely (<foreign>aṟa</foreign>) the expenditures (<foreign>cella</foreign> &gt; <foreign>celavu</foreign>) at hand (<foreign>kai</foreign>) (i.e. the expenses encountered) in the registration office (<foreign>āvaṇakkaḷiyē</foreign>), having made (<foreign>ceyitu</foreign> &gt; <foreign>ceytu</foreign>) the sale document (<foreign>vilaiyāvaṇam</foreign>), we the Sabhā of Ciṟupaḻuvūr, a <foreign>brahmadeya</foreign>, gave (<foreign>kuṭuttōm</foreign>); for the one <foreign>mā</foreign> (<foreign>orumāvum</foreign>) of this land (<foreign>innilam</foreign>), this only (<foreign>ituvē</foreign>) has to be (<foreign>āvatākavum</foreign>) the sale document (<foreign>vilai-y-ōlai</foreign>); the document for expenditures (<foreign>poruḷ cilav-ōlai</foreign>, lit. palm leaf for expenditures (<foreign>cilavu</foreign>) of money (<foreign>poruḷ</foreign>)); this only (<foreign>ituvē</foreign>) has to be (<foreign>āvatākavum</foreign>) the final settlement document (<foreign>poruḷ</foreign> <foreign>māvaṟuti</foreign>)<foreign> </foreign>and except these (<foreign>ituvalatu</foreign> &gt; <foreign>itu-v-allatu</foreign>) final settlement document (<foreign>poruḷ</foreign> <foreign>māvaṟuti</foreign>)<foreign> </foreign>and document for expenditures (<foreign>poruḷ cilav-elai &gt; poruḷ cilav-ōlai</foreign>) they do not have to show (<foreign>kāṭṭak kaṭavar allātānākavum</foreign>) [any] other (<foreign>vēṟu</foreign>) [document]; having thus (<foreign>ippaṭi</foreign>) agreed (<foreign>icaiñcu</foreign> &gt; <foreign>icaintu</foreign>), having taken (<foreign>koṇṭu</foreign>) this one <foreign>kācu</foreign> (<foreign>ikkācu oṉṟum</foreign>), having sold (<foreign>viṟṟu</foreign>) for a full (<foreign>aṟa</foreign>) price (<foreign>vilaikku</foreign>) one whole <foreign>mā</foreign> (<foreign>orumāvum</foreign>) of this land (<foreign>innilam</foreign>), we have taken (<foreign>koṇṭōm</foreign>) the complete (<foreign>aṟa</foreign>) money (<foreign>poruḷ</foreign>), we the Sabhā of Ciṟupaḻuvūr; upon their (<foreign>ivarkaḷ</foreign>) order (<foreign>paṇikka</foreign>), I have written (<foreign>eḻutinēn</foreign>) this document (<foreign>ippiramāṇam</foreign>), I the Madhyastan, lord (<foreign>uṭaiyān</foreign>) of Paḻuvūr, I of the thousand two hundred (<foreign>āyiratt-iru-nūṟṟuvan</foreign>),<note>In the PIM, #58 also mentions one man belonging to this group. This may be a group of Brahmins or, as Charlotte Schmid suggested to me, a group of merchants.</note> Muṭikoṇṭān; for this order (<foreign>ippaṭikku</foreign>) this is my signing (<foreign>enn-eḻuttu</foreign>) of those (<foreign>ivai</foreign>), I Pālāciriyan Ilakkuvaṇaṉ of Cāntamaṅkalam; for this order (<foreign>ippaṭikku</foreign>) this is my signing (<foreign>enn-eḻuttu</foreign>) of those (<foreign>ivai</foreign>), I Cavānti Nārāṇan of Paḻuvūr; for this order (<foreign>ippaṭikku</foreign>) this is my signing (<foreign>enn-eḻuttu</foreign>) of those (<foreign>ivai</foreign>), Cānti Palāciriyan Vīranārāyaṇantu; this [is the signing of] Cāvānti Nārāyaṇan Māṟan Pusyaiñai; I know (<foreign>aṟivēn</foreign>) this order (<foreign>ippaṭi</foreign>), I lord (<foreign>uṭaiyānēn</foreign>) of Tiruvāyikkulam, Nārāyaṇan, who performs (<foreign>paṇṇum</foreign>) the sacred service (<foreign>tiru-v-ārātanē</foreign>) of the temple (<foreign>kōyil</foreign>) of Vīracōḻa Viṇṇakār Āḻvār of this town (<foreign>ivvūr</foreign>);<note>May this temple be the still-standing Viṣṇu temple of Kīḻappaḻuvūr (see Map 2)?</note> I know (<foreign>aṟivēn</foreign>) this order (<foreign>ippaṭi</foreign>), the blacksmith (<foreign>karumakan</foreign>?) of this town (<foreign>ivvūr</foreign>). This is under the protection of the Panmāheśvaras.</p></div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

 <p>Reported in <bibl><ptr target="bib:ARIE1923-1924"/></bibl> (ARIE/1923-1924/C/1924/***).</p>
 <p>Edited and translated in <bibl><ptr target="bib:Gillet2024_01"/></bibl>, based on autopsy and photographs (<ref target="https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/****">by Valérie Gillet, 2016-2018</ref>).</p>
 <p>This digital edition by Valérie Gillet and Emmanuel Francis.</p>

 <listBibl type="primary">
 <bibl>
 <ptr target="bib:Gillet2024_01"/>
 <citedRange unit="page">TBC</citedRange>
 <citedRange unit="item">TBC</citedRange>
 </bibl>
 </listBibl>

 <listBibl type="secondary">
 <bibl>
 <ptr target="bib:ARIE1923-1924"/>
 <citedRange unit="page">TBC</citedRange>
 <citedRange unit="appendix">C/1924</citedRange>
 <citedRange unit="item">TBC</citedRange>
 </bibl>

 </listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
