<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_Schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_SQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Mēlappaḻuvūr, *** temple, time of ***, year **</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>author of digital edition</resp>
					<persName ref="part:vagi">
 <forename>Valérie</forename>
						<surname>Gillet</surname>
 </persName>
 <persName ref="part:emfr">
 	<forename>Emmanuel</forename>
 <surname>Francis</surname>
 </persName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris, CEIAS</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_INSMelKil00122</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
						<idno/>
					</msIdentifier>
					<msContents>
						<summary><p>#122. a) Tiruvālantuṟai Mahādeva temple, inner compound wall; b) on the southern outer face of the compound wall; c) personally located and read in situ; d) ARE 1895, no. 102; SII 5, no. 663; e) 11th regnal year and 302 days of Tribhuvana Cakkaravattikaḷ Śrī Rājādhirājadevar; f) Rājādhirāja I or II; g) inscription read with G. Vijayavenugopal.</p>

</summary>
					</msContents>
					<physDesc>
						<handDesc>
							<p/>
						</handDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:emfr" when="0000-00-00" status="draft">Further conversion of digital encoding to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
			<change who="part:mime" when="2025-06-10" status="draft">Conversion to DHARMA encoding scheme according to EGD (Encoding Guide for Diplomatic Editions)</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
		<body>

<div type="edition" xml:lang="tam-Latn" rendition="class:tamil maturity:vernacular">

<p>
<lb n="1"/><hi rend="grantha">svasti śrī</hi> <hi rend="grantha">tribhu</hi>vanac cakkaravattikaḷ <hi rend="grantha">śrīrājādhi</hi>rā<hi rend="grantha">jade</hi>vaṟku yāṇṭu patinonṟu nāḷ muṉnūṟṟiraṇṭiṉāl kunṟakkūṟṟamāna Uttuṅkatuṅkavaḷaṉāṭṭu
<lb n="2"/>ciṟupaḻuvūr Uṭaiyār koyil tevakanmikkum śrī mā<hi rend="grantha">heśva</hi>rak kaṇkāṇiceyvārkaḷukkum vanta tirumukappaṭi <hi rend="grantha">tribhu</hi>vaṉac ca
<lb n="3"/>kkaravatti konerinmai koṇṭān kunṟakkūṟṟamāna Uttuṅkatuṅkavaḷanāṭṭu ciṟupaḻuvūrt tiruvālantuṟaiy uṭai
<lb n="4"/>yār koyil tevakanmikkum<hi rend="grantha">śrīmāheśvara</hi>k kaṇkāṇiceyvārkaḷukkum Ittevaṟku veṇṭum nimantaṅkaḷukku Iṟuppatā
<lb n="5"/>ka vāṇakappāṭiy uṭaiyāṉ Arayaṉ viracoḻanāṉ yātavarāyaṉai nittoṟppaṭi Iṟaiyili māṟiṉa Innāṭṭuk kiṭacārāṉa vāra
<lb n="6"/>ṇavāci niccayitta māṭai Eḻupatum munpu kāṇiyuṭaiya manṟāṭikaḷukke kāṇiyāy patinoṉṟuvatu pacāṉa mutal Antarāyam pāṭṭam uḷpa
<lb n="7"/>ṭa tevatānam Iṟaiyiliyāka Iṭṭu variyilārum varik[kūṟu]ceyvārkaḷum Eḻuttiṭṭa Uḷvari taracconṉom Ivvūrp patinonṟāvatu pacāna mutal An
<lb n="8"/>tarāyam pāṭṭam uṭpaṭat tevatānam Iṟaiyiliyāka kaikkoṇṭu nimantañ celuttap paṇṇuka Eḻutiṉān tirumantira O[lai] Irā<hi rend="grantha">jentra</hi>ciṅkamuven
<lb n="9"/>taveḷān Eḻuttiṭṭār nilakaṅkarayarum tipat[ta]rayarum kankarāyarum nantipa[n]marum villavarāyarum vāṇātarāyarum nuḷamparāyarum Eḻuttiṭṭatu Itu<hi rend="grantha">panmāheśva</hi>ra<hi rend="grantha"> </hi>ra<hi rend="grantha">kṣai </hi>||
</p>

</div>

<div type="apparatus">

</div>

<div type="translation" source="bib:Gillet2024_01">

<p>Fortune! Prosperity! This is the 11th year and three hundred and two days (<foreign>muṉnūṟṟiraṇṭiṉāl</foreign>) of Tribhuvana Cakkaravartikaḷ Śrī Rājādhirājadevar. To the Tēvakaṉmis (<foreign>tēvakanmikkum</foreign>) of the temple (<foreign>kōyil</foreign>) of the Lord (<foreign>uṭaiyār</foreign>) of Ciṟupaḻuvūr of Uttuṅkatuṅkavaḷanāṭu alias Kuṉṟakkūṟṟam (<foreign>kunṟakkūṟṟam</foreign> &gt; <foreign>kuṉṟakkūṟṟam</foreign>) and to those who do the superintendence (<foreign>kaṇkāṇi ceyvārkaḷukkum</foreign>) of the Śrī Māheśvaras (the Śaiva group), the royal order (<foreign>tirumukappaṭi</foreign>) [of] Tribhuvaṉa Cakaravatti Kōnerinmai Koṇṭān has come (<foreign>vanta</foreign>); to the Tēvakaṉmis (<foreign>tēvakanmikkum</foreign>) of the temple (<foreign>kōyil</foreign>) of the Lord (<foreign>uṭaiyār</foreign>) of Ciṟupaḻuvūr of Uttuṅkatuṅkavaḷanāṭu alias Kuṉṟakkūṟṟam (<foreign>kunṟakkūṟṟam</foreign> &gt; <foreign>kuṉṟakkūṟṟam</foreign>) and to those who do the superintendence (<foreign>kaṇkāṇi ceyvārkaḷukkum</foreign>) of the Śrī Māheśvaras, to pay (<foreign>iṟuppatāka</foreign>) for the endowments (<foreign>nimantaṅkaḷukku</foreign>) wanted (<foreign>vēṇṭum</foreign>) for this god (<foreign>ittēvaṟku</foreign>), as <foreign>kāṇi</foreign> (<foreign>kāṇiyāy</foreign>) for the shepherds (<foreign>manṟāṭikaḷukkē</foreign> &gt; <foreign>maṉṟāṭikaḷukkē</foreign>) who possessed (<foreign>uṭaiya</foreign>) the <foreign>kāṇi</foreign> previously (<foreign>munpu</foreign>), seventy (<foreign>eḻupaṭum</foreign>) coins (<foreign>māṭai</foreign>) ascertained (<foreign>niccayitta</foreign>) by Kiṭacārāṉ Vāraṇavāci of this country (<foreign>innāṭṭu</foreign>), which changed (<foreign>māṟiṉa</foreign>) to tax-free (<foreign>iṟaiyili</foreign>) as per the everyday expenses (<foreign>nīttoṟppaṭi</foreign>) [by?] the lord (<foreign>uṭaiyāṉ</foreign>) of Vāṇakappāṭi, Arayaṉ Vīracōḻanāṉ Yātavarāyaṉ, having set (<foreign>iṭṭu</foreign>) as tax-free (<foreign>iṟaiyiliyāka</foreign>) <foreign>devadāna</foreign> (<foreign>tēvatānam</foreign>) including (<foreign>uḷpaṭa</foreign>) the <foreign>pāṭṭam</foreign>-tax (tax on land) and the <foreign>antārayam</foreign>-tax (tax levied by the local bodies) from (<foreign>mutal</foreign>) the crop (<foreign>pacāṉa</foreign>) of the 11th year, we said to give (<foreign>tarac</foreign>-<foreign>conṉōm</foreign> &gt; <foreign>coṉṉōm</foreign>) the local tax (<foreign>uḷvari</foreign>) which was recorded (<foreign>eḻuttiṭṭa</foreign>) [by] the revenue collectors (<foreign>variyilār</foreign>) and the officials who fix the taxes (<foreign>varikkūruceyvārkaḷum</foreign> &gt; <foreign>varikkukkūruceyvārkaḷum</foreign>); having taken in hand (<foreign>kaikkoṇṭu</foreign>) as a tax-free (<foreign>iṟaiyiliyāka</foreign>) <foreign>devadāna</foreign> including (<foreign>uḷpaṭa</foreign>) the <foreign>pāṭṭam</foreign>-tax and the <foreign>antārayam</foreign>-tax from (<foreign>mutal</foreign>) the crop (<foreign>pacāṉa</foreign>) of the 11th year in this town (<foreign>ivvūr</foreign>), to make (<foreign>paṇṇuka</foreign>) [them] observe (<foreign>celutta</foreign>) the endowment (<foreign>nimantañ</foreign>), Rājentraciṅkamuventavēḷāṉ recorded (<foreign>eḻutiṉāṉ</foreign>) the royal order (<foreign>tirumantiram</foreign>) on palm-leaf (<foreign>ōlai</foreign>). The signatories (<foreign>eḻuttiṭṭār</foreign>) [are]: that has been signed (<foreign>eḻuttiṭṭatu</foreign>) [by] Nīlakaṅkarayar, Tipattarayar, Kankarāyar, Nantipanmar, Villavarāyar, Vāṇāratāyar and Nuḷamparāyar. This is under the protection of the Panmāheśvaras.</p></div>

<div type="commentary">

</div>

<div type="bibliography">

 <p>Reported in <bibl><ptr target="bib:ARIE1923-1924"/></bibl> (ARIE/1923-1924/C/1924/***).</p>
 <p>Edited and translated in <bibl><ptr target="bib:Gillet2024_01"/></bibl>, based on autopsy and photographs (<ref target="https://didomena.ehess.fr/concern/data_sets/****">by Valérie Gillet, 2016-2018</ref>).</p>
 <p>This digital edition by Valérie Gillet and Emmanuel Francis.</p>

 <listBibl type="primary">
 <bibl>
 <ptr target="bib:Gillet2024_01"/>
 <citedRange unit="page">TBC</citedRange>
 <citedRange unit="item">TBC</citedRange>
 </bibl>
 </listBibl>

 <listBibl type="secondary">
 <bibl>
 <ptr target="bib:ARIE1923-1924"/>
 <citedRange unit="page">TBC</citedRange>
 <citedRange unit="appendix">C/1924</citedRange>
 <citedRange unit="item">TBC</citedRange>
 </bibl>

 </listBibl>

</div>

	</body>
</text>
</TEI>
